one of the first things we learn about
operating systems is that they act as
intermediaries sitting between hardware
and user programs this means user
programs cannot access Hardware
resources without the intervention of
the operating system if we think about
it both operating systems and user
programs are software after all they are
all built using programming languages
but if that's the case why can't user
programs overpower the operating system
and take control of the computer today
we're going to explore how a clever
cooperation between hardware and
software contributes to the robustness
of modern operating
systems hi friends my name is George and
this is core
dumped before we begin I want to clarify
that much of the information in this
video has been simplified for easier
understanding neither the
implementations nor the assembly code
shown correspond to any real platform or
architecture this is one of those rare
occasions where software alone is not
enough to solve a problem so Hardware
support is needed as you may know every
computer processor has a specific set of
actions it can perform called the
instruction set of the processor if we
want to give one software more control
of the system than another software we
can define a subset of special
instructions that not all processes can
use many architectures Define what is
known as privileged instructions to
enforce this the hardware must support
different operational modes and the
common approach to do that is is to use
a special onebit register that can hold
either a one or a
zero this register is called the mode
bit when its value is set to one the
processor is said to be running in
privileged mode which means it can
execute any instruction in the
instruction set including privileged
instructions when the value is set to
zero the processor runs in restricted
mode meaning it cannot execute
privileged
instructions as we know the CPU
internally uses combinational logic
circuits to decode incoming
instructions the mode bit has little to
no effect on normal instructions because
they can be run regardless of the
operational
mode however when it comes to privileged
instructions the value held in the mode
bit determines whether the running
process is allowed to execute
them in this way privileged instructions
can only be executed if the processor is
operating in privileged
mode and here the question that might
come to mind is how or who can flip the
value of the mode bit this is perhaps
the most delicate part of the mechanism
because if any user process could simply
switch to privileged mode the feature
would be pointless there might be
several ways to handle it but the
switching mechanism is typically
implemented through
interrupts let's set aside the mode bit
for a moment to explain what an
interrupt
is when a processor runs a program the
address register points to the memory
address of the next instruction to
execute
an interrupt is like a signal sent to
the CPU notifying it that an event has
occurred for example if the user presses
a key or moves the mouse an interrupt
can be triggered to make the system
react to the event when the signal is
received it causes the processor to
pause the current process and jump to a
specific memory
location this memory location contains
the executable code that the CPU will
use to handle the
interrupt this routine can be divided
into four steps first the CPU needs code
to save the state of the interrupted
process then there's code to handle the
interrupt for example calling a routine
to print a string after the interrupt is
handled the CPU executes code to restore
the state of the interrupted process
finally the CPU executes a special
instruction called interrupt return
which allows it to jump back to the
interrupted process and resume its
execution that's the basic flow of how
an interrupt works it temporarily halts
the current process and transfers
control to another
routine now back to the bit mode
interrupts can be used not only to make
the cpu's program counter jump but also
to automatically flip the value of the
mode bit to one this means that whatever
code resides at that memory location
gains control of the CPU and it does so
in privileged mode and here's something
I want to make sure is very clear any
executable entity could be loaded into
this memory region a web browser a text
editor anything this this is why we must
be extremely careful once this entity
gains privilege mode it can do virtually
anything within the computer and that
includes making sure that no other
process gains privilege mode the modern
approach is to ensure that the operating
system is loaded there so it can use
privilege instructions to maintain
complete control of the
system processors that support
operational modes were designed
specifically for this privileged mode is
meant to be used by the operating
systems kernel which is why it is
commonly known as kernel mode
restricted mode on the other hand is
meant for user programs preventing them
from overpowering the operating system
for this reason it is commonly referred
to as user mode now let's take a look at
some things that kernel mode can do but
user mode
cannot the most obvious example is
interacting with IO devices like Network
and graphics cards hard drives and
peripherals such as monitors and
keyboards direct manipulation of these
devices requires privileged instructions
meaning the CP U can only do it while
running in kernel
mode when it comes to memory privileged
instructions allow the manipulation of a
special Hardware component called the
memory management unit this unit is
responsible for limiting the physical
memory regions that the CPU can access
having control of the mmu means having
complete control over memory that's why
the operating system can read and write
anywhere in physical memory including
the address space of user programs
another thing privileged instructions
allow is the ability to red Define how
interrupts are handled as I explained
earlier interrupts cause the CPU to jump
to a specific memory location that
contains the routine necessary to handle
the interrupt the issue is that memory
isn't always used the same way and the
code to handle an interrupt might not
always be loaded in the same location as
mentioned earlier it would be dangerous
if an interrupt caused the CPU to switch
to Kernel mode and land in the address
space of a user process that's why
privileged instructions are useful they
allow the operating system to find the
exact memory location the CPU must jump
to when an interrupt is
triggered and because the memory
management unit can only be manipulated
through privileged instructions the
operating system uses it to ensure that
user processes cannot access the memory
locations where interrupt handlers are
stored this prevents any malicious
process from overriding the interrupt
handlers and attempting to take control
of the system in kernel mode we have
full control over the interrupt flow of
the CPU and by now youve likely noticed
that while the hardware provides the
tools it's ultimately up to the software
and by this I mean the operating system
to use them correctly to maintain
control of the
system and these are just a few examples
of things that programs running in user
mode cannot
do user programs are still allowed to
use a wide range of instructions in user
mode programs can perform essential
tasks like moving and copying data
executing arithmetic floating point and
bitwise operations eval valuating
conditions and running
Loops however imagine if programs
couldn't do basic things like reading
files displaying text on the screen or
sending messages over the network user
programs still need to access Hardware
in some way otherwise they wouldn't be
very useful so how do they manage that
the answer after a quick message from
neit code solving endless programming
problems won't get you far without
proper guidance if you're looking to
sharpen your problem solving skills and
crush your next technical interview neat
code. offers structured interactive
courses on data structures and
algorithms with a mix of videos articles
animations and practice problems neat
code makes learning more effective
personally I find it way more enjoyable
than other platforms because each lesson
builds upon the previous one and by the
time you reach more advanced topics
you'll have a solid foundation rather
than just a warning tag saying that you
probably won't make it remember NE code.
and if you want support me and get a
discount when you sign up you can use
the link in the description
below you've probably heard about
apis to allow user programs to access
Hardware resources operating systems
provide a set of functions in the form
of a library these functions are known
as system calls and they are essential
for user programs for example if a user
program needs to work with files it will
need a system call to open the file more
system calls each time it wants to read
or write to the file and another system
call to close the file when the work is
done system calls are still functions
which means they must have an internal
implementation that is eventually
compiled into machine code but here's
where things start to seem a bit strange
because these functions are part of a
library when we write user programs and
use these functions they become part of
our source code this means they'll
become part of our user program when
compiled but that doesn't quite add up
because we just established that user
programs run in user mode and therefore
cannot use the privileged instructions
required to manipulate
Hardware so what's really going on here
if we take a closer look we'll notice
that at some point inside these system
call functions there's an instruction
that triggers an interrupt yes
interrupts can be triggered not only by
Hardware but also through software in
this case the int instruction causes the
program to trigger an interrupt which
makes the program counter jump to a
routine in the operating system's
address space remember when an interrupt
occurs the CPU switches to Kernel mode
allowing the routine to execute all the
privileged instructions necessary to
manipulate hardware and fulfill the
system call once the required privileged
instructions have been executed it's
necessary to return control to the
interrupted process and ensure that the
mode bit is set back to zero so that the
program resumes execution in user mode
as
intended how this is done can vary
across
architectures in this example it's
handled by the interrupt return
instruction but in other architectures a
separate instruction might be required
to switch the operational mode involving
a dedicated instruction or explicitly
overwriting the mode bit followed by
another instruction to return control to
the interrupted
process another way to visualize this is
that part of the function resides in the
address space of the user program
running in user mode while another part
resides in the operating systems address
space and runs in kernel
mode in general terms we could say that
system calls provide essential services
to user programs I originally planned to
make a separate video about system calls
but I think I can cover the rest here
including the pros and
cons the most important advantage of
system calls is the hardware abstraction
they provide to developers many people
have no idea how difficult and complex
it is to directly manipulate Hardware
since system calls handle Hardware
interactions for us when we require
access to Hardware resources we as
developers only need to invoke them
system calls are incredibly useful
because they allow us to think in terms
of code not
transistors another significant
Advantage is security this is closely
tied to Hardware abstraction directly
manipulating Hardware is prone to errors
which can lead to vulnerabilities and
system malfunctions a common question
from people transitioning from languages
like python or JavaScript to low-level
programming is could I fry my computer
the answer is always no because the
operating system manages hardware for us
even if we write a very bad C program we
won't be able to directly manipulate the
hardware in a way that could damage our
computer the third Advantage is
portability if multiple platforms follow
certain guidelines the same source code
can compile in different
systems system calls have some drawbacks
the first one being performance overhead
this is also somewhat related to the
hardware abstraction that they provide
interrupts which system calls rely on
are not cheap in terms of performance
they require extra steps such as context
switching and modern architectures with
features like caching can further
increase the performance
cost also when a program invokes a
system call it effectively interrupts
itself to pass control to the operating
system once the OS gains control there's
no guarantee that it will immediately
handle the system call the operating
system may use this opportunity to
perform other tasks like running the CPU
scheduler or managing other system
resources eventually the system call
will be attended to but for the user
program there's no guarantee it will
happen
quickly from a certain perspective
system calls can be seen as traps the
hardware abstraction is the bait that
lures user programs into giving control
back to the operating
system another con is platform
dependency which contradicts the
portability Pro I mentioned earlier
while many platforms aim for
compatibility some weird variations
exists Microsoft okay
okay summarizing the CPU operational
modes the mechanism is simple user
programs can use interrupts to make the
CPU switch to Kernel mode but at the
cost of interrupting themselves and
handing control of the CPU to the
operating system the operating system in
turn can use a privileged instruction to
resume an interrupted process but forces
it to continue running in user
mode the concept of system calls has
been so successful that some
architectures have made invoking them
Easier by providing dedicated
instructions eliminating the need to
manually set up interrupts for this
reason in many architectures you can
find the CIS call instruction and the
cisr privileged instruction they also
make assembly code more
readable when an operating system relies
on the cooperation of user programs to
regain control and perform management
tasks it is classified as a
non-preemptive or cooperative operating
system this type of general purpose
operating system is no longer used
because there is a big problem with them
think about a program that contains an
infinite Loop without any system calls
inside the CPU will remain stuck
executing the loop
indefinitely if a process intentionally
or unintentionally avoids using system
calls the CPU will never return control
to the operating system effectively
starving all other
processes once again software alone
cannot solve this problem Hardware
support is necessary
the solution involves using a timer when
the timer expires it triggers a hardware
interrupt this timer is built into the
CPU and can only be controlled through
privileged
instructions before allocating the CPU
to a user process the operating system
sets the timer and while the process
runs the timer is counting down user
processes can still voluntarily return
control to the operating system via
system calls however if a process takes
too long to invoke a system call the
timer ensures that eventually an
interrupt will be triggered forcing the
process to stop and giving control back
to the operating
system this mechanism allows kernel mode
to exert complete control over how much
CPU Time Each process is allowed to
use in addition when a CPU supports
operational modes the hardware must be
able to react if a user program attempts
to directly manipulate Hardware if the
processor is running in user mode and en
counters a privileged instruction the
hardware can be configured to trigger an
interrupt immediately passing control to
the operating system so it can handle
the suspicious behavior of the user
program most likely terminating its
execution interrupts are a fundamental
feature of the CPU so it's more accurate
to say that kernel mode grants complete
control over how the CPU is
used when the hardware architecture
supports these features and the
operating system leverages them we are
talking about preemptive operating in
systems with all of that in mind we
should Now understand that both user
programs and the operating system are
just
software since user programs are
confined to user mode they cannot
directly interact with the hardware
instead they must pass control to the
operating system which manipulates the
hardware on their
behalf so the idea that the operating
system is always in the middle is just a
very high Lev abstraction of what's
truly
happening many might wonder if software
other than the operating system can run
in kernel mode the answer is yes for
example when a new graphics card is
released the operating system may not
know how to control it as it was
developed before the card even
existed operating system developers
can't write code for every single
Hardware device that exists so this task
is usually left to the hardware
manufacturers
the solution is called drivers software
designed to control specific
Hardware since controlling Hardware
requires privileged instructions drivers
must run in kernel mode when a user
program needs the hardware the operating
system uses the appropriate
driver however this technique comes with
a serious drawback any code running in
kernel mode has access to privileged
instructions which makes it impossible
for the operating system to fully
isolate it from other processes or even
from itself as a result all code running
in kernel mode shares a single address
space If a driver mistakenly writes to
the wrong memory address it could
corrupt data critical to the operating
system and if a driver crashes it will
take the entire operating system down
with it without the operating system
user programs can't function and the
whole system goes down this is why
drivers with bugs often cause blue
screen of death in
Windows despite the risks allowing code
to run in kernel mode is necessary
because drivers are essential again it's
virtually impossible for OS developers
to write code for every single Hardware
device out there but the fact that
third-party code can run in kernel mode
has led to its use for purposes Beyond
just device drivers this includes things
like video game anti-cheating systems
and malware detection software let me
quickly explain why this happens first
software running in kernel mode doesn't
rely on system calls which allows it to
run considerably faster than if it were
running in user mode imagine a game that
bans controllers to prevent unfair
advantages over mouse and keyboard
players a player might cheat by using a
controller mapped to keyboard inputs via
a thirdparty
program since the game runs in user mode
it can't tell whether the input is truly
from a keyboard however anti-cheating
software in kernel mode can directly
monitor Hardware activity detecting if
input is actually coming from a
controller for malware detection kernel
mode allows software to scan devices
like network cards monitoring Network
traffic and inspect the address space of
running processes to check for
suspicious activity such as monitoring
private data and sending it to an
untrusted
endpoint now it makes sense why this
kind of software must run in kernel mode
if it ran in user mode they wouldn't be
able to do what they do using kernel
mode for everything isn't always a good
idea though take for example crowd
strike a malware detection software
installed on millions of business
devices worldwide in September an update
corrupted a configuration file filling
it with zeros with the file damaged the
software crashed causing operating
systems to crash as well the result
worldwide chaos thousands of devices
showing the blue screen of death and
billions of dollars in business
losses another example is Vanguard an
anti-cheating software from Riot games
used in popular games like League of
Legends and valerant when first released
it caused blue screens of death for
hundreds of players but the scarier part
is its connection to tensent a Chinese
company that owns Riot
games it turns out you can't play Riot
games without installing Vanguard which
makes sense for anti-cheating purposes
the annoying part is that Vanguard runs
in kernel mode even when you're not
playing meaning it could monitor
everything you do on your computer while
there's no evidence it does the fact
that 10cent is a Chinese company likely
subject to government oversight rais
raes privacy concerns considering
Vanguard runs on millions of computers
worldwide this becomes quite
unsettling and that wraps it up for now
if you want to learn more about this
whole kernel level software situation
from a cyber security expert I highly
recommend checking out this videos from
lowlevel one of my favorite channels a
huge thanks to NE code for sponsoring
this video don't forget to check it out
and if you learned something today don't
forget to like And subscribe until next
time I George