this video was sponsored by
skillshare when a process is running it
continuously uses the CPU to execute
instructions one after another during
this process the result of executing an
instruction depends on the entire
context in which that instruction is
being executed especially on the state
of the
registers the same instruction can
produce different results depending on
the values held in those
registers when talking about concurrency
if a process is interrupted the CPU
can't s simply be given to the next
process because the data stored in the
registers at that moment belongs to the
interrupted process if the new process
were to resume execution without
handling this properly it would operate
in the wrong context with incorrect
data therefore every time a process is
interrupted to allocate the CPU to
another process the state of the
registers must be captured and stored in
memory and the state of the new process
must be loaded so it can continue
execution correctly this is known as a
context switch and it's called that
because we are changing the context in
which the CPU is operating the problem
is that this doesn't just magically
happen as I'm showing you in this
animation the operating system actually
needs to run some code to accomplish
this every time I've mentioned this
concept in one of my previous videos
someone in the comments asks how this
process is achieved without altering the
state of the interrupted process so
today we are going to answer that
question hi friends my name is George
and this is core dumped
it's important to note that we are going
to talk about interrupt based switching
in a very simple CPU that doesn't
provide an interrupt handling mechanism
like the one we built a few episodes ago
context switching depends entirely on
software in such systems each program is
responsible for storing its own State
before giving up the CPU to other
programs fortunately for us those kinds
of CPUs are quite rare because they are
neither safe nor particularly useful
interrupts sometimes also called traps
are an essential feature of computers
the legendary Moz 6502 one of the most
popular CPUs of all time and nearly 50
years old had interrupts even
microcontrollers which are designed to
be simple processors for controlling
Electronics have interrupts computers
with an interrupt mechanism have been
with us for more than 70 years so yeah
computers wouldn't be the same without
them as we already know a process can be
interrupted in two ways it can
voluntarily interrupt a Itself by
triggering a software interrupt or
executing a special instruction to ask
the OS for a
resource or it can be interrupted by a
signal from a hardware component such as
a timer if it takes too long to release
the CPU or an IO
device in both cases the effect of the
interrupt is the same the CPU finishes
executing the current instruction to
prevent inconsistencies and then the
program counter is immediately
overwritten making it jump to a specific
memory location this memory M location
contains the executable code needed to
handle the interrupt including the code
required to capture the state of the
interrupted process notice that even
before fetching those instructions the
program counter has already been
overwritten by the interrupt meaning we
no longer know where the process was
interrupted unfortunately we can't avoid
this problem as we'll see in a moment
but before that let's think about the
code needed to capture the CPU state of
the interrupted process to keep things
simple we'll write it in
code to start we need to capture the
values in the general purpose registers
so the interrupt Handler routine could
begin with some instructions like these
this requires dealing with specific
memory locations reserved for this
purpose which can be tedious to avoid
that it's easier to push the values onto
the stack the flags are also important
so let's say we push those onto the
stack as well and the same goes for the
stack pointer itself but wait the stack
pointer is currently pointing to the
user program stack that's a huge problem
because these instructions are meant to
be executed by the operating system
which has its own stack yes that's right
remember the OS is also software so it
has its own stack executing these
instructions would modify the stack of
the interrupted
process well maybe we could start
handling the interrupt by modifying the
stack pointer so that the register state
is pushed onto the kernel stack but now
we've overwritten the stack pointer
before saving its value to avoid that we
could store the stack pointer value into
a memory location before modifying the
stack pointer and then simply push the
value from that memory
region and we could spend hours fixing
little details like this in the most
convenient way in fact I'm pretty sure
some of you are already thinking about
other ways to do it but ultimately the
issue of the program counter being
overwritten by the interrupt itself
makes this problem impossible to solve
at least by software because there's no
instruction we could run right at the
beginning to save that value of course
not by the time the CPU runs the first
instruction that value is gone this is
one of those rare but exciting
situations we encounter on this channel
when Hardware needs to support software
and not the other way around we'll cover
that right after a quick message from
skillshare something not a lot of you
know is that I've been working on a book
but since I've never done self-editing
or publishing before I needed to learn
how and skillshare made it easier than I
ever imagined skillshare is one of the
largest online learning communities for
creatives offering thousands of expert L
classes across film development
illustration design freelancing
productivity and more whether you're
looking to level up your career develop
a new skill or explore a passion project
skillshare has you covered plus there
are lessons from hundreds of popular
content creators so you can learn
directly from the people who inspire you
just a few weeks ago I was still writing
my book in Word but now I'm doing it the
right way with professional software
designed for authors and it only took me
a a few hours to get up to speed thanks
to skillshare it's all about making the
choice to learn grow and invest in your
creative journey and I'm currently
learning from this class with Marcus
brownley where he shares his skills in
content creation including script
writing filming and editing so if you've
been wanting to pick up a new skill
now's the perfect time the first 500
people to use my link in the description
will get a one-month free trial of
skillshare don't miss out join today and
start learning
and now back to the
video any architecture that supports
interrupts should provide a mechanism to
prevent losing the state of the
interrupted process in other words it
should offer at least minimal Hardware
support to ensure the software preserves
the program counter of the interrupted
process there are two main solutions for
handling interrupts keep in mind that
each architecture has its own way of
doing it and these are just two general
approaches the first approach is the
easiest to understand instead of
depending on a single Reg set the CPU
can provide multiple register
sets multiple register sets can be
assigned to different processes this way
when a process is interrupted the next
process can simply switch to another
register set avoiding any modifications
to the state of the previous
process however there may be more
processes than available register sets
and since registers are part of the
hardware we can't increase them at
runtime but here's the thing we don't
need an infinite number of register sets
two is more than enough if the CPU
supports operational modes one of the
register sets can be shared by multiple
user programs while the other is only
accessible to the operating system in
kernel mode remember while the CPU is
running in kernel mode it can do
virtually anything in this situation
that means the OS can manipulate and
access the additional register set for
convenience let's call these the common
register set and the privileged register
set when an interrupt occurs the CP
switches to Kernel mode deactivates the
common register set and starts using the
privileged register set ensuring that
the state of the interrupted process
remains
unmodified this way the interrupt won't
overwrite the program counter on the
common register set but on the privilege
register set special privileged
instructions allow the OS to access the
disabled registers and copy their values
into the currently enabled
registers after each one of these
instructions a normal instruction moves
the value just fetched from the disabled
register into a memory location this can
be the stack as we attempted in the
first part of the video but eventually
it will be copied into the process
control block of the interrupted process
of course this involves extra
instructions not shown here to look up
where the PCB is stored in memory next
the PCB of another process is read and
the opposite process occurs normal
instructions copy values from memory
into the active register set followed by
privileged instructions that transfer
that data into the disabled register
finally a privilege instruction is used
to set the timer if preemptive
scheduling is used and then the cisr
privileged instruction is executed in
this type of architecture cisr does two
things swaps the active register set
locking the user program into using one
of them and switches back to user mode
since instructions are now executed on
the common register set in the next
cycle the CPU resumes execution of the
elected process pretty easy right
unfortunately this approach is not very
popular especially among modern
architectures I'm not a hardware expert
so I can't give a definitive reason but
my best guess is that it's not worth it
to duplicate the exact same circuitry on
the CPU die especially now that modern
architectures have hundreds of registers
and even more complex components like SD
registers also as some of you might have
noticed it isn't really necessary to
duplicate the entire register set it
should be enough to have a separate set
for only critical registers like the
stack pointer and the program counter as
we discussed in the first part of this
video Let's explore other options what
if we could automate part of the process
in Hardware minimizing the amount of
software needed I won't go into too much
detail here since each architecture
implements this differently but in
general this is done in two
ways instead of duplicating register
sets the hardware can automate certain
steps these steps function like
hardwired instructions built directly
into the
CPU just as we sometimes hardcode things
like a database URL or a private key and
source code instead of fetching them
from an environment file instructions
and data can also be hardwired into the
CPU circuitry this allows them to be
executed right before an interrupt takes
effect one approach is to ensure that
the operating systems stack pointer is
always accessible to the CPU either
through a memory location hardwired to
the CPU or a special
register when an interrupt occurs
critical registers like the program
counter and the stack pointer are
automatically pushed onto the OS stack
right before the program counter is
overwritten to jump to the interrupt
Handler from this point forward it's the
software's responsibility to preserve
the rest of the registers we must be
careful not to write to any registers
before copying their content into memory
which is exactly what we attempted to do
in the first part of this video except
now the program counter and stack
pointer of the interrupted process are
safe thanks to Hardware
support and then we have crazy
architectures that take things even
further performing most of the context
switch entirely in
Hardware this is usually achieved
through a segment register that points
to a memory region managed by the
operating system where a special data
structure
resides in some architectures this data
structure is known as the task State
segment or TSS and the corresponding
register is called the task register in
very simple terms whenever an interrupt
occurs the CPU automatically copies the
entire content of all registers and
pastes it into the task State segment so
let me quote myself from the beginning
of this video when I said the problem is
that this doesn't just magically happen
as I'm showing you in this animation
Well turns out it can magically happen
at least from the software's point of
view this is huge because it makes this
whole video kind of pointless except for
the fact that for some reason major
operating systems avoid using this
feature of course this is actually more
complicated than I'm making it seem so
if you'd like me to cover specific
architectures like X 8664 or arm let me
know in the comments before ending this
video just wanted to let you know that
my friends over at COD Crafters have
added new challenge-based courses
including this one on how to create an
interpreter from scratch so you can
start creating your own programming
language I'll leave you a link in the
description if you want to support me by
subscribing and that's it for now there
are more exciting topics coming soon so
make sure to subscribe you won't want to
miss it if you enjoyed this video or
learned something new please hit the
like button it's free and it helps me
out a lot see you in the next one