this video was sponsored by
jetbrains what I'm showing here looks
like an image but it's actually a
program I'm using two processes to
render a fractal the part implemented in
Rust performs the mathematical
calculations to determine the color of
each pixel in the fractal it adds this
data to an array and once all pixel
calculations are complete it triggers an
event sending the array as a message in
typescript I listen for that event
receive the data and then pass it to a
function that draws the pixels on an
HTML canvas
applications like this one built in a
modular way are possible thanks to
interprocess
Communications today we will talk about
how processes which are isolated by
default can interact with other
processes by exchanging
information hi friends my name is George
and this is core dumped in a previous
episode we learned that when a program
is loaded into memory to begin execution
it receives a new name a
process but a process is more than just
executable code loaded into memory it
also includes a CPU State the memory
region allocated to the process a list
of open files and other resources such
as IO devices thus a process is not just
a program it's the entire context in
which the program
operates this isolation however
introduces a significant drawback as
there are many scenarios in which a
process needs to cooperate with others
if processes were entirely isolated
there would be no way for them to coll
elaborate so processes can be classified
based on whether they cooperate with
other processes a process can be either
independent or
cooperating two processes that share
data between them are clearly
cooperating processes but there are
additional reasons for enabling process
cooperation for example computational
speed up in systems that support
parallelism complex tasks can be divided
into smaller ones that can be executed
simultaneously reducing the total time
required to complete the larger task or
modularity constructing a system in a
modular way allows for the division of
system functions into separate
processes but notice that in both cases
processes need a way to coordinate their
activities to function correctly
cooperating processes require a
mechanism for interprocess communication
that enables them to exchange data
sending and receiving information
between each
other there are two fundamental models
of interprocess
communication shared memory and message
passing we will discuss how both
interprocess communication mechanisms
work along with examples from Modern
operating
systems let's start with shared memory
as the name suggests this mechanism
allows processes to share a memory space
directly remember when multiple
processes are running on a system the
operating system allocates a separate
block of memory for each one this is
known as the processes address space
through a mechanism called privilege
instructions the the operating system
enforces isolation preventing processes
from accessing each other's memory if a
process attempts to read or write to
another process's address space the
operating system will immediately
interrupt and terminate that process
enforcing the isolation policy to ensure
data safety so to allow two or more
processes to share a memory area the
operating system requires them to agree
to remove this
restriction typically a shared memory
region is created using system calls and
resides in the address space of the
process that created it any process
wishing to communicate through this
region must attach it to its own address
space Also through system
calls once the shared memory region is
established both processes can
communicate by writing to and reading
from this shared
area here's an important detail once the
operating system grants the shared
memory region it no longer manages what
the processes do with it what I mean is
that the way the data is structured and
the specific locations within the shared
region where that data is written are
entirely determined by the processes not
the operating
system for example consider a producer
consumer model where one process the
producer generates data and the other
the consumer reads it suppose the shared
region contains an array where the
producer writes 8 bit signed
numbers if the consumer reads these as
unsigned 8bit numbers it will interpret
the exact same bits but with a different
meaning
similarly if the consumer expects a
different data type like an unsigned
32-bit integer or reads from the wrong
address misinterpretations will
occur as you can see there's a lot that
can go wrong here the consumer must know
precisely how the data is structured and
where it's being written failing to
follow these conventions could lead to
failures in one or both processes or
Worse undefined
Behavior the processes are also
responsible for ensuring they don't
write to the same location at the same
time otherwise they could encounter race
conditions an issue we will cover in a
future episode on thread
synchronization okay but are there
popular programs that use shared memory
I'll share the answer after a quick
message from jet brains if you're a
developer just learning self-educating
or working on personal projects setting
up your entire development environment
might not be the most productive way to
use your time you might need a full IDE
loaded with all the tools you need right
out of the box
that's where jet brains products come in
with Ryder and webstorm you get just
that and I'm glad to tell you that you
can now access the full versions of
these idees for free for non-commercial
use whether you're developing games
building web apps or exploring theet
ecosystem Ryder offers all the tools you
need including full support for Unity
unreal asp.net and more webstorm is the
ideal IDE for modern JavaScript and
typescript development supporting
Frameworks like like react nodejs
angular and so much more this is perfect
for those of you who want to grow create
and stay productive both idees come
loaded with features like code analysis
safe refactoring project-wide navigation
and Version Control giving you
everything you need to work efficiently
and write great
code getting started is simple just
download writer or webstorm pick a free
non-commercial license and you're all
set head to the link in the description
to start your devel Journey with jet
brains and now back to the
video you might have noticed that when
using Chrome multiple processes are
created even if you're only using a
single tab any chromium based browser is
a perfect example of a modular system
which relies on interprocess
communication as we know dynamic web
pages often contain JavaScript which can
sometimes come with bugs that could
potentially crash the
browser to address this problem chromium
uses a shared memory approach roach
dividing tasks among three types of
processes browser renderer and plug-in
processes the browser process manages
the user interface and IO operations and
is created only once when Chrome starts
renderer processes handle webpage
content such as HTML JavaScript and
images with a new renderer process for
each open Tab and plug-in processes
manage specific plugins like flash
QuickTime or PDF
readers this isolation ensures that if
one tab crashes only its renderer
process fails leaving other tabs
unaffected other examples of systems
that use share memory are simulation
software game engines databases
Management systems and deep learning
Frameworks now let's talk about the
second approach message passing sharing
memory isn't always the best way for
processes to communicate as it can be
error prone and might Place more
responsibility on the programmers than
they're comfortable with an alternative
method is for the operating system to
provide a mechanism that allows
processes to communicate and synchronize
their actions without sharing the same
address space address spaces can remain
isolated and instead of writing to
memory processes can communicate by
sending
messages popular message passing
mechanisms include pipes sockets and
remote procedure calls although the
specific implementations of these
mechanisms are beyond the scope of this
video the general concept is as follows
a message passing facility provides a
set of basic operations for for instance
suppose we have two processes A and B if
process a wants to send messages to
process B it must invoke a system call
to request that the operating system
establish a link with process B this
link serves as The Logical pathway
through which messages are sent and
notice that I just said logical path
what is actually happening is that the
operating system's kernel creates a Quee
in its own address space and this Quee
will serve as a mailbox where process a
can send messages and process B can
receive them the behavior of this queue
can vary based on communication
requirements for instance we may need
asynchronous instead of synchronous
communication or a buffered cue if we
want to limit the number of messages the
mailbox can
hold for full duplex communication a
mailbox can be implemented with two cues
allowing both processes to send messages
to each other simultaneously without
conflict but some of you might have
already noticed that there's something
odd here since the mailbox resides in
the operating system address space
processes shouldn't be able to access it
and yes that is true processes cannot
directly read or write to mailboxes thus
the operating system must provide system
calls for at least two operations send
and
receive when process a needs to send a
message to process B it uses a system
call to instruct the operating system I
need to place this message in the
mailbox shared with process B but I
cannot access it directly so please
handle this for
me because the mailbox exists in the
Colonel's address space the operating
system can copy the message to the
mailbox similarly when process B wants
to check for messages it uses its
corresponding system call to ask the
operating system I cannot read the
mailbox shared with process a directly
could you please check if there are any
messages for me if there's a message the
operating system can return it as the
return value of the function
if you don't fully understand why system
calls are necessary for this process I
highly recommend reviewing the previous
videos in this series and this is the
general idea behind message passing
Communications one of the first
operating systems to introduce the idea
of shared mailboxes was match an OS
whose derivatives form the foundation of
some Modern systems including iOS and
Macos match treated processes as tasks
and had a very specific name for
mailboxes ports it's important to
remember that messages are sent to Ports
not directly to
processes this distinction matters
because two processes can have more than
one communication link and not all ports
are associated with exactly two
processes a process may keep an open
port to receive messages from any other
process this type of Port is known as a
listening port and its purpose is to
handle special messages called
connection requests to establish new
private communication links between
processes some of these Concepts May
have started to sound familiar you see
message passing has a huge advantage
since it doesn't require two processes
to share their address space processes
don't even need to be on the same
machine to
communicate of course this requires a
more complex underlying implementation
such as networking capabilities to
establish a connection between computers
this involves driver level programming
for components like network interface
cards but if implemented correctly at
the operating system level the process
should be seamless for Developers
message passing between processes on
different machines will function the
same way as it does between processes on
the same
machine the client server architecture
is typically implemented using the
socket interface which is an example of
a message passing mechanism supported by
nearly all mainstream operating systems
today it is usually Illustrated this way
although I'm not sure I completely agree
as it suggests that the clients and
server are machines in reality they are
simply processes running on those
machines and communication doesn't
always require a network the client and
server processes can run on the same
machine as we see when using Local Host
to test
projects anyway when a client sends a
request to a server the IP address
identifies the machine hosting the
server process while the port represents
the mailbox through which the server
process receives
requests servers providing specific
services like http P FTP or SSH rely on
the socket interface which makes me
remind the guys from codec Crafters have
a nice challenge-based course where you
can learn how to use sockets to
implement an HTTP server from scratch in
the programming language of your choice
I'll leave a link in the description in
case you want to support me when
subscribing unfortunately message
passing systems do have drawbacks
because ports reside in the Colonel's
address space processes must use system
calls each time they want to send or
receive messages this can be quite
costly in terms of
performance this limitation does not
apply to the shared memory approach with
shared memory system calls are only
necessary when creating the shared
region and attaching processes to it
once these steps are complete processes
can read from and write to the shared
region as if it were part of their own
address space without needing further
system calls this results in
communication that is extremely fast
essentially as fast as direct memory
access and just to clarify I'm not
saying that message passing is slow
shared memory is simply faster in 99% of
cases message passing is more than
sufficient and if you learned something
today don't forget to like And subscribe
see you in the next one