This video was sponsored by
Brilliant. There's something oddly
satisfying about watching CPU usage
spike to 100% during a benchmark test.
But one thing that always caught my
attention when I was younger was that
even though the CPU is completely maxed
out, the system doesn't become
unusable. This is mainly because general
purpose operating systems prioritize
response time, ensuring that interactive
applications stay smooth even under
heavy load.
Today we're going to talk about the
CPUuler, one of the most important
components of any operating
system. Hi friends, my name is George
and this is core
dumped. Before starting, please consider
giving a like to this video if you
enjoyed it or learned something. This
episode is longer than usual and it was
hard to edit, but it is full of
information. So here's the content table
in case you need to jump to a specific
topic. CPU scheduling is a technique
used by operating systems to determine
which task or process gets to use the
CPU at a given time based on specific
criteria. One important criterion is
response time as mentioned in the
introduction. However, depending on the
system, other criteria might also be
important such as CPU utilization,
throughput, turnaround time, and waiting
time. We will explore these concepts
throughout the video. We are going to
start by building a very simple
scheduler. By far the simplest CPU
scheduling algorithm is the first come
first serve scheduling algorithm. With
this scheme, the CPU is allocated to the
first process that requested it. To
begin with, we must be clear about what
it means to allocate the CPU to a
process. When a program is executed, it
becomes a process and the operating
system reserves a memory block for it.
Within this block, there's a memory
segment called the text section which
contains the executable code for the
program. Each process has its own
dedicated text
section. From our computer architecture
from scratch course, we know that the
CPU contains a special register called
the address register, also known as the
program counter. This register points to
the next instruction to be executed.
When we say the CPU is allocated to a
process, it means that this register is
pointing to the text section of that
process enabling the CPU to execute
instructions from it. When the CPU is
reallocated to another process, the
operating system modifies the address
register so it points to the executable
code of the new process. This involves a
more complex operation called a context
switch, which we've covered with more
details in previous episodes.
Another important concept to understand
is that processes aren't concrete
entities like objects or instances of
structures in the traditional computer
science sense. Instead, processes are
contexts in which the computer operates.
To manage these processes, the operating
system uses a special structure called
the process control block or PCB.
This strct is not the process itself,
but rather a representation of it
containing all the necessary information
about the process such as its state,
program counter, registers, and other
management
data. Every time a process is created,
the operating system generates a process
control block to keep track of that new
process. The implementation of the first
come first serve policy is easily
managed with a FIFO Q which makes sense
here because it operates on the
principle that the first element added
to the queue is the first one to be
removed. But we cannot directly push
processes into this queue because
processes are abstract contexts and
cannot be treated as discrete elements
of any data structure. Instead, what the
operating system does is push the
process control block of each process
into the queue. Throughout this video,
I'll represent PCBs as boxes. And you'll
often, if not almost always, hear me
refer to them as processes. But remember
that what enters the queue isn't
actually a process, but its process
control block. In first come, first
serve. When a process is created, its
process control block is pushed onto the
tail of the que. When the CPU is free,
it is allocated to the process at the
head of the queue. Sounds simple, right?
Well, not quite. There's a lot we're
overlooking. For starters, we are
assuming that a process can only get the
CPU once the previous process has
completed its
execution. This causes a lot of
problems. First, not all processes
terminate. Many applications such as
servers or background services are
designed to run indefinitely. If we
allocate the CPU to a process that never
ends, all subsequent processes would be
indefinitely waiting in the queue.
And second, if we assume that a process
can only get the CPU once the previous
process finishes its execution, we
ignore an important fact. Programs in
execution don't use the CPU
continuously. If a task takes 2 minutes
to execute, it doesn't mean it kept the
CPU busy for the entire 2 minutes.
During execution, there are often
periods where the program is waiting for
something
else. To illustrate this, let's break it
down with an example program. after a
quick message from
Brilliant. As developers, one of our
main goals should be to improve our
problemsolving abilities. With
Brilliant, you gain access to dozens of
interactive courses designed by experts,
enabling you to learn by doing rather
than just reading. Their first
principles approach helps you build a
deep understanding from the ground up.
Each lesson is packed with hands-on
problem-solving activities that allow
you to engage with concepts, a method
proven to be six times more effective
than simply watching lecture videos.
Brilliant is also available on your
phone, making it easy to build real
knowledge in just a few minutes a day,
unlike mindlessly scrolling through
PDFs. Their latest courses, including
applied Python, creative coding, and
thinking in code, are perfect for
building foundational skills and
learning real world
applications, helping you to develop the
mindset to think like a programmer and
begin creating complex programs to build
games and apps. You can try for free 30
days of Brilliant Premium and get a 20%
discount on your annual subscription by
scanning the code on the screen or by
visiting
brilliant.org/coredumpted also linked in
the description below. And now back to
the
video. This program opens two text
files, one containing text and the other
empty. Its purpose is to copy the
content from one file to the other. But
to avoid using a lot of memory, it
copies data in chunks. let's say eight
bytes at a
time. We're particularly interested in
the part of the program where the
copying happens. If we were to observe
the instructions being executed by the
computer, it would look like
this. Now, it might initially seem like
these instructions are executed like
this. But if we were to represent it
more accurately, it would look quite
different. Something more like this.
Reading from and writing to files
requires the program to invoke the
operating system as file manipulation
involves interacting with hardware, in
this case the disk. In other words,
reading and writing involve IO
operations. The real problem here is
that IO operations are usually costly in
terms of performance. They can take a
lot to complete.
These instructions right here simply
cannot be executed immediately after the
previous one. Not until the IO operation
managed by the system call is completed,
which entirely depends on the IO
hardware capabilities, not the CPU. As a
result, the program doesn't use the CPU
continuously. If we were to map CPU
usage of a program over time, we would
see gaps where the CPU remains idle,
waiting for IO operations to finish
before continuing execution.
These gaps are not the exception but the
norm at least in systems based on the
vonoman architecture which represents
over 99% of modern computers. In fact,
this behavior is so common that it has
been continuously studied for
decades. Those lapses when a program is
using the CPU are called CPU bursts
while those time-lapses when the program
is waiting for an IO operation to
complete are called IO bursts. Every
process execution begins with a CPU
burst. that is followed by an IO burst
which is followed by another CPU burst
then another IO burst and so on.
Eventually the final CPU burst ends with
a system request to terminate execution.
As I mentioned earlier, this behavior
has been studied for decades as the
success of CPU scheduling largely
depends on it. The durations of CPU
bursts have been extensively measured.
And while they vary between processes
and systems, they tend to follow a
predictable distribution that looks like
this. This next part is very important.
Before continuing, take a moment to
pause the video and analyze what this
chart
represents. The chart shows that most
processes have a large number of short
CPU bursts and only a small number of
long CPU bursts. This is a critical
observation for designing CPU scheduling
algorithms because it highlights that
processes often spend significant time
waiting for IO operations. If a
scheduling algorithm doesn't account for
this behavior, a lot of CPU time will be
wasted. So when a process enters an IO
burst, ideally the CPU should be
allocated to a different process, one
that isn't also waiting for IO
operations.
One of the main goals of CPU scheduling
is to keep the CPU as busy as possible,
allowing processes to run as fast as
they can while sharing the
CPU. Notice that a process's CPU burst
never starts immediately after the
previous one ends. There is always a
small additional process in between
which I've represented in gray. I'll
come back to this in a moment. What's
important to understand right now is
that a scheduling algorithm must take
this into account. Instead of allocating
the CPU to a process until it fully
terminates, theuler should allocate it
only until the process's current CPU
burst ends. Achieving this behavior, of
course, makes the implementation of
ouruler a little more complex because
now we need to consider that processes
can be in different states. Every
process begins in the new state. A new
process is a program that has just been
launched, but its executable file is
still being loaded into memory. Once the
program is fully loaded and all
necessary resources are allocated, the
process enters the ready state, meaning
it is prepared to execute, but is
waiting for CPU time. When the CPU is
assigned to a process, it enters the
running
state. At some point, the process will
likely make a system call, such as an IO
request, which voluntarily returns
control of the CPU to the operating
system. Keep in mind that an IO call is
not only made to request some resource,
like manipulating a file or allocating
memory, but to simply wait for some
event to happen, such as an user
keystroke or an incoming network
request. In both cases, the process
moves to the waiting state until the
event happens or the IO operation is
completed. Once the request is
fulfilled, the process becomes ready
again, waiting for theuler to allocate
CPU
time. Notice that even when the IO
operation is completed, the process does
not immediately resume execution. This
happens because while the process was
waiting, the CPU has most likely been
allocated to another process. So even
though it is now ready to continue
running, it must wait for its turn. For
most of their lifetime, processes cycle
between these three states: ready,
running, and waiting. Some processes,
such as web servers, are designed never
to terminate and remain in this cycle
indefinitely. But for most user
programs, the process eventually enters
the terminated
state. These names are arbitrary and
they vary across operating systems. The
states that they represent are found on
all systems. However, certain operating
systems also more finely delineate
process states. For example, a
terminated process may not be really
terminated. After making a system call
to exit, the operating system must free
allocated resources, including memory.
Some operating systems make a clear
distinction between a process that has
been fully terminated and one that is
still in the process of termination.
This state model explains why cues are
the fundamental data structure used in
CPU scheduling. Even though there is a
specific waiting state, processes in
other states except the running state
are also waiting. Given that hundreds of
processes may be waiting at any moment,
using cues to manage their execution
order is both logical and
efficient. It is important to realize
that only one process can be running on
a processor core at any given time. This
means that while a Q makes sense for
waiting processes, it does not apply to
the running process. When studying CPU
scheduling algorithms, it is necessary
to be aware of another component of the
operating system, the
dispatcher. When a running process
enters an IO waiting state and the CPU
becomes available, the dispatcher steps
in with one single purpose. Allocate the
CPU to the process at the head of the
ready Q. In other words, perform the
context switch. Although the running
process is not stored in any queue, a
reference to its process control block
is always maintained. This allows the
dispatcher to save the CPU state into
the PCB when an interruption occurs.
This saved state enables the process to
resume execution later. The dispatcher
then places the PCB into the waiting
queue. Next, after handling the
interrupted process, the dispatcher
retrieves the PCB of the next process
from the head of the ready Q, identifies
it as the new running process, restores
its previous CPU state, including
registers and the program counter, and
reallocates the CPU, allowing the
process to resume execution from where
it was interrupted. If the processor
supports it, the dispatcher is also
responsible for switching to user mode
before handing control to the process.
In other words, the scheduler determines
which process should use the CPU next by
managing the ready Q according to a
specific scheduling policy while the
dispatcher is responsible for the
execution of the decision made by
theuler. These additional CPU bursts
caused by the dispatcher are inevitable
since the CPU itself is required to
execute the context switch. This delay
is known as dispatch latency, the time
it takes for the dispatcher to stop one
process and start another. Because the
dispatcher is invoked during every
context switch, it must be as fast as
possible. For this reason, the
dispatcher is one of the most highly
optimized components of an operating
system. Since it is implicit, the
dispatch latency is usually not
illustrated between
processes. By the way, this is a variant
of something known as a Gant chart, a
bar chart that illustrates a specific
schedule showing the start and finish
times of each participating
process. In first come firsts served
scheduling. This policy is implemented
using a FIFO Q as the ready Q. As soon
as a process makes an IO request, the
CPU is immediately allocated to the
process at the head of the
queue. Notice that the name first come
first served can be somewhat ambiguous
because the scheduler is not actually
managing entire processes but rather
their next CPU burst. A more precise
name would be first CPU burst come first
served.
That said, since many books and
resources continue to refer to it as
first come, first served, we'll stick
with that convention. And with that, we
have the simplest CPU scheduling
algorithm. But while it does take CPU
utilization into account, that doesn't
mean it's effective at optimizing it. To
understand why, let's go back to our CPU
burst frequency graph. Notice that while
very large CPU bursts are rare, their
probability is never zero.
The most common processes, those with a
high number of short CPU bursts, are
known as IObound processes. These
processes depend heavily on IO
operations, meaning their performance
would improve if the IO subsystem were
faster. But it is also possible to have
processes that exhibit a high number of
long CPU bursts. Unlike IObound
processes, these processes do not
benefit significantly from a faster IO
subsystem, but instead they depend on
faster CPU speeds and for that reason
these are called CPUbound processes. The
problem with CPUbounded processes and
the first come first serve scheduling
algorithm is that they can generate a
negative effect on CPU
utilization. Imagine we have one
CPUbound process and some IObound
processes. For convenience, I'm going to
use the same color for the IO bound
processes. The CPUbound process will get
and hold the CPU for a relatively long
time. During this time, all the other
processes will finish their IO and will
move into the ready Q, waiting for the
CPU. While the processes wait in the
ready Q, the IO devices are idle.
Eventually, the CPUbound process
finishes its CPU burst and moves to an
IO device. All the IObound processes
which have short CPU bursts execute
quickly and move back to the IOQ cues.
At this point, there's no process to
dispatch and the CPU sits idle. The
CPUbound process will then move back to
the ready Q and be allocated the CPU
again. All the IO processes end up
waiting in the ready Q until the
CPUbound process is
done. See the problem here? There is a
convoy effect as all the other processes
wait for the one big process to get off
the CPU. This effect results in lower
CPU and device utilization than might be
possible if the shorter processes were
allowed to go
first. Yes, the shorted job first
scheduling algorithm exists and is the
next one we are going to
learn. Shortest job first assigns the
CPU to the process with the shortest
next CPU burst. If two processes have
the same burst length, first come first
served is used as a
tiebreaker. Again, note that a more
precise name would be shortest next CPU
burst first scheduling since it
prioritizes the next CPU burst rather
than the total process length. Most
people in books refer to it as shortest
job first. So once again, let's stick to
that convention.
This algorithm can be implemented using
a priority queue where priority is
determined by the length of the next CPU
burst of the waiting processes. This
allows those short CPU burst processes
to overtake those CPU hungry processes
reducing the convoy effect. This
algorithm is also provably optimal in
that it gives the minimum average
waiting time for a given set of
processes. Imagine we have four
processes that arrive almost
simultaneously. The first process next
CPU burst takes 2 minutes to complete
while the others only take a few
milliseconds each. In first come first
serve. If those shorter CPU bursts
arrive just after the long CPU burst,
they would experience significant delays
because they'd have to wait for the
longer to
finish. On the other hand, if processes
with short CPU burst are allowed to go
first, their waiting times would be
minimal and the process with the longer
CPU burst would barely be affected. it
would simply start a few milliseconds
later, which would make little
difference to it. Moving a short process
before a long one decreases the waiting
time of the short process more than it
increases the waiting time of the long
process. Consequently, the average
waiting time
decreases. Minimizing the average
waiting time in a system is crucial
because it represents the time that
processes are ready to run but cannot
execute as they wait for their turn to
use the CPU.
There are important considerations to
keep in mind whenever auler relies on
priority cues as we'll explore later.
But there's one major issue specifically
tied to shortest jobs first. It is
impossible to implement
perfectly because unless we could see
the future, there is no way to know the
exact length of a process's next CPU
burst.
You might think that we could use the
program counter to determine where the
next system call occurs and how long the
process will use the CPU before its next
IO burst. However, this approach is
unreliable because between the current
instruction and the next system call,
there can be loops or function calls
that alter execution time. The program's
execution path may depend on external
inputs like the user input, making
prediction even harder. For example,
this function takes an user input,
convert it to uppercase, and then print
it. The amount of iterations depends on
the length of the user
input. Since we cannot know the exact
next CPU burst, the best we can do is
estimate it based on past CPU bursts
with the assumption that the next CPU
burst will likely be similar in length
to previous ones. To approximate this
value, we compute an estimate using an
exponential average of previously
measured CPU bursts.
I know this isn't rocket science, but if
you're not into math, I'll break it
down. First, it's important to
understand that each process's CPU burst
prediction depends only on its own
history. Other processes do not affect
its prediction. Each process's CPU
bursts form a sequence of observed
durations over
time. N is the most recent CPU burst. N
minus one is the previous CPU burst. N
minus2 is the one before that, and so
on. n +1 is the next CPU burst, the one
we want to predict in the formula. That
means toao subn is the predicted burst
time for the process in the most recent
iteration while t subn is the actual
burst time that was observed. So to subn
+ 1 is the estimated CPU burst duration
for the next
iteration. Since to subn represents the
previous prediction, we can expand the
formula
recursively. Since to subn minus one is
the prediction before that we can expand
it
again and then with subn minus2 and so
on. What this shows is that this term
retains the process's past history. As a
result, we don't need to store an entire
list of possibly thousands of CPU burst
durations. We only need to keep the most
recent
prediction. And what about this
parameter
alpha? Well, if alpha equals zero, the
most recent CPU burst is completely
ignored and the prediction relies only
on past history.
If alpha equals 1, the prediction is
based only on the most recent CPU burst,
ignoring all past
history. Thus, alpha controls the
relative weight of the recent and the
past history in our prediction. A common
choice is alpha equals 1/2 which gives
equal weight to recent and past
history. And notice that this doesn't
mean all observed CPU burst in the
history are equally weighted. By
expanding the formula, we can see that
each CPU burst duration is multiplied by
alpha * 1 - alpha raised to a power.
Since alpha is between 0 and 1, the term
1 - alpha decreases exponentially,
meaning older CPU bursts have less
influence on the
prediction. This makes sense because
older execution patterns are less
relevant when predicting future CPU
bursts. Additionally, when a process is
first created, there is no historical
data. In this case, the initial
prediction is typically set to a
constant value defined by the operating
system or based on the systemwide
average. For example, using a starting
value of 100 milliseconds results in a
predicted next CPU burst of around 72
milliseconds, which as you can see is
closer to recent CPU bursts than the
oldest
ones. Here's a chart comparing the
predicted versus observed CPU bursts
over a longer period of time. While not
perfect, this approach provides a decent
approximation. But there's an important
decision the dispatcher must make that
we haven't discussed yet. Imagine
process A enters the ready Q with a
specific next CPU burst and is
eventually allowed to run. Then an
instant later, process B enters the
ready Q, but process A is still running.
The question is if the remaining CPU
burst of process A is longer than the
next CPU burst of process B, should
process A be interrupted to give
priority to process B? This decision
depends on theuler. If auler allows
running processes to be interrupted, we
are dealing with a preemptive scheduling
algorithm where the operating system can
preempt currently executing processes.
In contrast, a non-premptive will never
preempt a running process. Even if a
process with a shorter CPU burst arrives
in the ready queue, it will have to wait
until the running process completes its
CPU burst and releases the
CPU. This is not a trivial decision as
the execution order of processes can
change depending on whether the shortest
job first algorithm is preemptive or
non-premptive. And now that we
understand preeemption, let's discuss
why it is the default choice in modern
systems.
Consider a non-premptive system where a
process with an extremely long next CPU
burst reaches the head of the ready Q
and is selected. Since the system is
non-premptive, there is no way to
interrupt this process until it
voluntarily releases the
CPU. But what if it never
does? Infinite loops are not uncommon in
computer science. If no system call is
used inside the loop, the process will
never return control of the CPU to the
OS.
This is problematic in general purpose
systems where concurrency is a key
feature. Remember, concurrency is a
technique that allows the CPU to
alternate execution between processes
very quickly, creating the illusion that
all processes are running
simultaneously. However, in
non-premptive systems, if a CPUbound
process holds the CPU indefinitely or
even for long periods, all other
processes freeze from the user's
perspective. This is a major issue
because non-premptive systems rely on
processes to behave correctly and return
control in a reasonable amount of time.
Malware could exploit this by
intentionally avoiding system calls to
monopolize CPU time. Whenever a
scheduling policy causes a process to
wait indefinitely in the ready queue,
this is called starvation because the
process is starving for CPU
time. Even CPUbound processes can suffer
from starvation. For example, in
shortest job first, a process with a
long estimated CPU burst may be forced
to stay in the queue indefinitely if
many shorter CPU bursts continue
arriving. The only way for this process
to get CPU time is if no other process
is in the ready queue. In real world
systems, this is unlikely since hundreds
of processes compete for CPU
time. In terms of concurrency, that
would look something like this. Thus,
starvation is not just about process
burst length, but rather a consequence
of the scheduling policy itself. While
shortest job first is efficient in terms
of CPU utilization and waiting time, a
general purpose operating system
requires other scheduling criteria as
well. A great example of preemptive
scheduling is the roundroin
algorithm. The roundrobin scheduling
algorithm is similar to first come
first-s serve scheduling. A FIFO Q is
used as a ready Q, but preeemption is
added to enable the system to switch
between processes. A small unit of time
called a time quantum or time slice is
defined. Here in this animation, I'm
using a time quantum of 100
milliseconds. New processes are added to
the tail of the ready Q. The CPUuler
picks the first process from the ready
Q, sets a timer to interrupt after
one-time quantum, and dispatches the
process. One of two things will then
happen. The process may have a CPU burst
of less than one time quantum. In this
case, the process itself will release
the CPU voluntarily. Theuler will then
proceed to the next process in the ready
Q. If the CPU burst of the currently
running process is longer than one-time
quantum, the timer will go off and will
cause an interrupt to the operating
system, forcing a context switch to be
executed and the process will be put at
the tail of the ready Q.
The dispatcher then selects the next
process in the ready queue. This routine
is applied consistently to every
dispatched process, ensuring that no
single process can hold onto the CPU for
long periods or indefinitely, which
prevents other processes from being
starved of CPU time. Something very
important to mention is that the timer
is a physical device, usually embedded
in the CPU circuitry, meaning preemptive
scheduling can only be implemented if
the hardware provides support for it.
There's a very cool video about this on
the channel. So, if you want to learn
more about the topic, go check it
out. Notice that when a process is
preempted, it does not enter the waiting
state since it did not request I/IO.
Instead, it goes directly into the ready
state waiting for its next time
quantum. If we need a scheduling policy
that fairly distributes CPU time,
roundroin is ideal. If there are n
processes in the queue and the time
quantum is q, each process receive one n
of the CPU time in chunks of at most q
time
units. This ensures that once a process
enters the ready queue, it will wait at
most n minus one q time units before its
next turn. But while roundroin ensures
fair distribution, waiting time is not
always optimal. If the time quantum is
too large, most processes will enter an
IO burst before being preempted, causing
roundroin to behave like first come
first
served. At first, it might seem like the
obvious solution is to simply reduce the
time quantum, but if the time quantum is
too small, processes will be interrupted
too frequently, causing a high number of
context switches.
And remember context switch time is pure
overhead because the system does no
useful work while switching. As a
result, processes will take longer to
complete due to excessive interruptions.
The CPU will spend more time switching
between processes than actually
executing
them. And here we need to start talking
about another scheduling criteria. The
turnaround time defined as the total
time taken from a process's creation to
its completion.
Mathematically, it is the sum of the
time spent waiting in the ready queue,
the time spent executing on the CPU, and
the time spent doing IO
operations. Another useful metric used
as scheduling criteria is the throughput
defined as the number of processes that
are completed per time
unit. Again, if the time quantum is
smaller than the average context switch
time, the CPU will be busy but
constantly switching between processes
rather than executing them. Maximizing
CPU utilization is meaningless if the
CPU is not doing useful work. A
well-designed scheduling algorithm must
balance CPU allocation and overhead to
optimize both turnaround time and
throughput. The average turnaround time
of a set of processes does not
necessarily improve as the time quantum
increases. Though as you can see here,
in general, the average turnaround time
can be improved if most processes finish
their next CPU burst in a single time
quantum to ensure context switches
happen only when
necessary. However, turnaround time is
not always the best criterion for
measuring scheduling efficacy. Often, a
process can start producing output
before completing execution. And as we
stated earlier, some processes may even
never terminate.
Thus, another important metric is the
response time defined as the time from
submission of a request to the first
response produced. This is not the total
time needed to complete execution of a
process, but rather how quickly it
starts responding. Response time is
critical because it directly affects
that smooth feeling that users expect
from interactive systems, especially
when
multitasking. Roundroin is one of the
simplest ways to achieve concurrency.
Each process gets a fixed time quantum
in a rotating fashion. Once a process
finishes its time quantum, the next
process is allowed to run. If this
rotation happens fast enough, the system
appears to be executing all processes
simultaneously. The only problem is that
all computer processors have a speed
limit. As the number of concurrent
processes increases, round robin
struggles to maintain responsiveness. At
some point, the number of processes will
be so high that each process will wait
much longer before getting CPU time. and
the illusion of simultaneous execution
breaks down as the average response time
increases. Decreasing the time quantum
might seem like a solution. After all,
it could make it look like processes
regain CPU time more frequently. But as
we've already discussed, reducing the
time quantum too much leads to excessive
context switches, which is just as
problematic. To deal with this issue,
there are three possible solutions.
increase the processor speed allowing
context switches to happen faster. So we
can use smaller time quantums without
negatively affecting turnaround time or
use multiple processors allowing
processes to run in parallel and share
the workload. However, both of these
require hardware upgrades which are not
always feasible. But the third solution
can be achieved through software alone
with a smarter
CPUuler. Think about the processes
running on your computer. You might be
playing a video game while streaming
with Outlook, a Gmail client, a file
explorer, and other background apps all
running simultaneously. So much stuff
that roundroin causes your game to lag a
bit. The question here is, do all these
processes really need the same amount of
CPU time? Probably not. If we assign
higher priority to the right processes,
we can increase their response time,
making them feel smooth and responsive
again from the user's perspective. Yes,
it's true that background processes will
get the CPU less often, but think about
it. Does it really matter if your email
notification is delayed by half a
second? That said, not all background
processes are trivial. Some, like
operating system services, are critical.
The key point is this. If we can
correctly identify which processes need
higher priority, we can significantly
improve overall system responsiveness
without upgrading the CPU or adding more
cores.
Priority scheduling is implemented using
a priority Q where each process is
assigned an integer value representing
its
priority. In this example, I'm using one
and zero to distinguish between high and
low priority, but the actual range of
priority values varies depending on the
operating system. Some systems may use a
range from 0 to 255. Others might go
from 0 to 32,000, especially when a
finer granularity of priority levels is
needed. Whether lower numbers represent
higher or lower priority also depends on
the system. In this animation, lower
values indicate higher
priority. It's also common to combine
multiple scheduling strategies. For
example, priority scheduling can be
combined with roundroin to ensure
fairness among processes with the same
priority.
One inherent issue with priority
scheduling is starvation. In a heavily
loaded system, a steady stream of higher
priority processes can prevent a low
priority process from ever getting the
CPU. If this sounds familiar, that's
because the shortest job first algorithm
is essentially a type of priority
scheduling where priority is based on
the inverse of the predicted next CPU
burst. Here's an interesting story. The
IBM 7094, a powerful mainframe computer
used by NASA and the US Air Force for
scientific and military applications,
was introduced in
1962. Rumor has it that when they shut
it down in 1973, they found a low
priority process that had been submitted
back in 1967 and had not yet been
run. A solution to the problem of
indefinite blockage of low priority
processes is aging. Aging involves
gradually increasing the priority of
processes that wait in the system for a
long time. For example, if priorities
range from 127 low to zero high, we
could periodically say every second
increase the priority of a waiting
process by one. Eventually, even a
process with an initial priority of 127
would have the highest priority in the
system and would be
executed with both priority and
roundroin scheduling. All processes may
be placed in a single queue, but
depending on how the cues are managed,
an O search may be necessary to
determine the highest priority
process. In practice, it is often easier
to have separate cues for each distinct
priority.
This is known as multi-level Q
scheduling. And here there must be
scheduling among the cues. One way is
the one being shown on the screen right
now. Each Q has absolute priority over
lower priority cues. Scheduling simply
dispatches the process in the highest
priority non-mpt
Q. But to avoid starving lower priority
cues, we could schedule cues in another
way. We can rotate the ready Q in a
roundroin fashion but dispatching a
different amount of processes in a row
depending on the priority of the queue
to time slice among the
cues. Multi-level Q scheduling is
commonly used to partition processes
into several separate cues based on the
process type making it better to
schedule processes with multiple
response time requirement. It even allow
us to use a different scheduling
algorithm for each Q. The foreground Q
might be scheduled by a roundroin
algorithm for example while the
background Q is scheduled by a first
come first serve
algorithm and that's basically what we
expect from a generalpurpose CPUuler to
give priority to interactive processes
but not to the point of starving lower
priority
ones. There's just one more issue to
address. In a typical multi-level Q
scheduling algorithm, processes are
permanently assigned to a queue when
they enter the system. This has the
advantage of low overhead, but it's also
inflexible because processes don't
behave the same way throughout their
lifetime. Take your email client for
example. Most of the time it runs
quietly in the background, occasionally
checking for new messages, but the
moment you bring it to the foreground,
you expect it to be fast and responsive.
Menus, buttons, forms, all need to react
instantly. A process's CPU usage pattern
and by extension its response time
requirements can change
dynamically. The multi-level feedback Q
algorithm was designed to adapt to these
dynamic changes in
behavior. Here's how it works. Every
process starts in the highest priority
queue. If a process completes its CPU
burst within a single time quantum, it
can return to that queue after finishing
its I/IO. If a process needs more CPU
time than allowed by the time quantum,
it's moved down to a lower priority
Q. Lower priority QES have larger time
quantums, and processes that behave more
like IO bound tasks can be moved back up
if they complete their CPU burst in less
time than the quantum assigned to the
higher priority
Q. Over time, processes that have short
CPU bursts will tend to stay in higher
priority cues. In contrast, CPUbound
processes will gradually sync to lower
priority cues. This is how the system
adjusts process priority based on
behavior
automatically. Keep in mind that this is
just one example of multi-level feedback
Q scheduling. It comes in many
variations or as I like to say all
colors and flavors. Not only can the
scheduling algorithm applied to each Q
differ, but also the criteria used to
decide when a process should be promoted
or demoted between cues.
For instance, instead of relying solely
on the most recently observed CPU burst
to adjust a process's priority, the
system could use a prediction based on
historical data, which might help
avoiding unnecessary Q switches in
response to isolated or unusual bursts,
whether extremely short or unexpectedly
long. If you've been paying attention,
you might be thinking, wait, aren't we
penalizing CPUbound processes just for
needing more CPU? It seems we are now
going against the original idea of
prioritizing more important processes.
Aging indeed can prevent starvation. But
still, once a process is recognized as
CPUbound, it will eventually be demoted.
What's the deal here? Well, this is very
hard to explain without a 40 minutes
master class on processes analysis. The
best I can do now is to highlight two
important facts.
IObound and interactive processes are
not necessarily the same thing, but both
are characterized by very short CPU
bursts. And second, modern processors
are extremely fast. If you open a task
manager right now, you'll see hundreds
of processes running. Yet, if you open a
resource monitor, you'll notice that
combined, they use less than 10% of
total CPU
time. These two facts reveal that most
of the time, higher priority cues are
actually empty. So when a process sinks
to the lowest priority queue, it's not
as doomed as it sounds. Being dispatched
without aging is actually more probable
than we might
think. Think about when your system is
under heavy load. For example, when
rendering a video or running a
benchmark, CPU usage hits 100%, but your
desktop stays smooth, your music keeps
playing, and your browser remains
responsive. That's because theuler
prioritizes everyday interactive tasks
while less frequent CPUheavy processes
get served with any CPU cycles left over
from higher priority
processes. If we put multi-level Q and
multi-level feedback Q side by side,
which one sounds more general purpose to
you? Many operating systems used some
variation of multi-level feedback Q in
the past, but modern systems face new
challenges. These factors introduced
additional complexity and more advanced
scheduling strategies were developed to
handle
them. In a future episode, we'll take a
closer look at how modern operating
systems handle CPU scheduling. We'll
explore the scheduling policies of
Linux, Windows, and BSD and how they
manage all these modern variables. And
that's it for now. An intuitive
introduction to CPU scheduling. Before
we wrap up, a few final clarifications.
Modern systems schedule threads, not
processes. This allows concurrency
within a single application. For
example, one thread handles the user
interface while another performs
background
computations. With multi-level feedback
Q, the user interface of a CPU hungry
process can remain smooth since the
thread that manages the UI can maintain
high priority independently of the
thread that performs the heavy
computations.
The IOQ shown in this video is
simplified. We've shown it as a FIFO Q
for clarity. In reality, the IO
subsystem is more complex. Processes
that enter the IOQ may finish in a
different order than they arrived. Just
like first come, first served is
inefficient for CPU scheduling. It's
also not ideal for IO devices. For
instance, a process needing to use a
graphics card shouldn't have to wait
behind another process that's currently
using the disc. All of these details,
however, concern to another component of
the operating system, the
IOER. Let's wrap things up for now.
There are more exciting topics coming
soon, like race conditions and thread
synchronization, so make sure to
subscribe. You won't want to miss it. If
you enjoyed this video or learned
something new, please hit the like
button. It's free and it helps me out a
lot. See you in the next one.