This video is sponsored by
Flexispot. Concurrency is a recurring
topic on this channel. It's the
technique alongside CPU scheduling that
distributes computing resources among
multiple executable entities. The system
switches the CPU between them so quickly
that it creates the illusion they are
all running at once. When these
processes operate independently,
everything tends to work smoothly. But
the moment concurrent entities need to
interact, things can get tricky and if
not handled carefully, the consequences
can be
disastrous. Today we're going to talk
about race conditions, one of the most
bizarre and elusive bugs you can
encounter in systems
programming. Hi friends, my name is
George and this is core dumped.
When we first learn programming, many of
us are told we're simply writing
instructions, defining one step after
another for the computer to follow to
reach a goal. What most beginners aren't
told is that each line of code doesn't
necessarily correspond to a single CPU
instruction. In practice, some lines
might compile down to just one
instruction, while others require many.
Adding two numbers, for example,
requires several instructions. one to
fetch each operin from memory into CPU
registers, another to tell the CPU to
add the values in those registers, and a
final instruction to store the result
back into memory so the value can be
accessed later. As good systems
programmers, we must keep in mind that
most operations we write in source code
require multiple CPU steps to accomplish
what we intend them to do. And this is
the first critical concept to know if
you want to understand race conditions.
Most operations are not atomic.
Now let's refresh some concepts we've
covered before. We've previously
discussed that threads are usually
created through system calls. In C, for
example, the most common way to create
threads is with the Pthread create
function available on PZIX compliant
systems. This function receives a
pointer to another
function. When we call Pthread create, a
lot happens under the hood. The inner
system call informs the operating system
that the function passed as a parameter
can start running as a separate
executable entity running concurrently
with the thread that made the call. So
in our example after the system call the
main function continues running without
waiting for the newly created thread to
finish. Also remember concurrency does
not imply parallelism. In a multi-core
system concurrent functions may execute
in parallel but on a single core system
the CPU core is shared. Each thread
takes turns. The switching happens so
quickly that it appears as if they're
running
simultaneously. There are many use cases
where threads and concurrency are
incredibly useful. For example, modern
HTTP servers rely heavily on threads to
handle multiple client requests at the
same
time. Without concurrency, the main
function would have to serve each client
request before even accepting another
client's request. You can imagine how
inefficient that would be.
With concurrency, the main thread
listens for incoming requests. And as
soon as one arrives, it spawns a new
thread to handle it. Since that thread
operates independently, the main thread
can go back to listening for new
requests. But despite how useful
concurrency is, it must be used with
caution. Let's say the server returns
the name of the client sent in the body
of the request. In this case, each
thread only deals with its own client
and doesn't interact with others. Since
there's no shared data, not much can go
wrong. But what if threads need to share
and modify the same data? Imagine that
instead of replying with the client's
name, the server returns a string shared
by all threads, one that's periodically
updated from a list of sentences by
another
thread. In this scenario, threads need
some way to communicate.
But almost everyone new to concurrency
will fail at implementing this
correctly. Many will define a global
variable to store the current string,
create a function that periodically
updates it, and spawn a thread that runs
this function. The writer thread simply
modifies this variable as needed, while
the handler threads read from it
whenever they need to respond to a
client. And this is exactly what I tried
on my own machine. I defined a shared
variable, hard-coded a list of
sentences, and the writer thread cycles
through that list, updating the shared
variable. To observe the behavior, I
logged every response that the handler
thread sent back to clients into a text
file. At first glance, everything looked
fine. The writer thread appeared to
update the string periodically. But then
I found
this. One response returned a string
that was not in the list I hard-coded.
For some reason, the last letter was
different. Something had clearly gone
wrong. Now, just looking at this single
instance isn't enough to draw
conclusions. It happened once in over 9
million requests. In fact, it would have
been nearly impossible to notice by
scrolling through the logs. I only found
it because I knew exactly what I was
looking for and wrote a program to
search for anomalies.
So, I ran the test again, this time for
much longer, and analyzed the results
with the same program. After nearly 85
million requests, I found more
suspicious outputs. And this time, the
issue was a little more
obvious. To make it clearer, I'll assign
a different color to each sentence from
the list so you can see exactly what's
happening. It turns out that in some
responses, the server was sending
combinations of different
sentences. So, what's going on here?
This is one of those rare cases where
the program misbehaves not because our
logic is flawed, but because we ignored
how the system works
underneath. We'll cover the source of
this error after a quick message from
today's sponsor,
Flexispot. As developers, most of us
spend long hours in front of a screen.
And while a good chair helps, eventually
your body just needs to
move. Being uncomfortable kills
productivity. I felt it, too. getting
up, walking away from work just to shake
off the
stiffness. Today's workspace demands
flexibility, and the Flexis Spot E7 Pro
standing desk delivers just that. The
intuitive keypad lets you save up to
four custom heights, so switching
between sitting and standing is
effortless. And check this out, the lift
is incredibly smooth and surprisingly
rock solid. No wobble at all. Its frame
is made from automotive grade steel and
the thickened legs support up to 440 lb,
enough for dual monitors, a full rig,
even me sitting on
it. And if you want to stay active
without leaving your setup, Flexispot
also offers this auto incline walking
treadmill. It fits perfectly under the
desk and lets you work, watch, or just
move while staying focused. It comes
with this useful remote control so you
set the speed, the incline angle, and of
course, safely stop it while using
it. If you are ready to elevate your
workday, visit flexispot.com to learn
more about the E7 Pro standing desk and
this treadmill. Both come with a solid
warranty and a 30-day free return
policy, making them a smart investment
in your health and productivity. I'll
leave a link in the description below.
And now back to the
video. To understand why our program is
behaving so strangely, we need to look
at how strings work. Believe it or not,
the string data type deserves its own
dedicated video. But for simplicity,
we're going to focus on C style strings.
In summary, in C, strings are
represented in memory as a sequence of
characters terminated by a special null
character.
This null character is convenient
because it eliminates the need to store
both a pointer and the string's length
as is done in some object-oriented
languages. What's pertinent to us right
now is that most string operations are
not atomic. For example, when printing a
string, the function iterates through
the characters one by one, outputting
them to the console until it encounters
the null
character. Similarly, copying a string
is a multi-step operation. If the string
is long enough, the computer can't
simply copy the entire array of
characters from one memory location to
another in a single step. Instead, it
has to loop through each character,
copying them one by one until it reaches
the null
terminator. Now, to speed up this
process, some architectures copy data in
chunks. But even then, those chunks have
a maximum size, and depending on the
length of the string, the operation may
still require multiple steps. For
simplicity, let's stick to the character
by character approach. The reason I
chose this example is that it clearly
demonstrates what's happening under the
hood. Just think about it. If one thread
is reading from the shared string while
another is writing to it, concurrency
can cause the operating system to
interrupt the writer midcopy to give the
CPU to another process. When this
happens, the shared string is said to be
in an invalid state because its current
value is something we never intended it
to be. And if the scheduler decides to
allocate the CPU to a thread that reads
this shared data before the writer
thread resumes and completes its update,
that thread will end up copying
inconsistent
data. And that's exactly what happened
in our example. While modifying the
string, the writer thread was
interrupted and the threads handling
client requests ended up copying the
string while it was still incomplete.
That's why all the errors show strings
composed of fragments from different
valid sentences in the
list. A race condition is a software bug
that occurs when the outcome of a
program depends on the unpredictable
order in which multiple threads or
processes access and modify shared
resources. Race conditions are typically
side effects of preemptive operating
systems. There lies the unpredictable
requirement for this kind of bug to
occur. For those unfamiliar, a
preemptive operating system is one that
forcibly interrupts running processes
from time to time so that other
processes can gain access to the CPU.
This is how the system distributes
computing resources fairly among all
active programs. When we talked about
CPU scheduling, we mentioned the time
quantum, a fixed amount of time that
defines how long a process or thread can
use the CPU before it may be
interrupted. Through system calls,
processes and threads can voluntarily
yield control of the CPU to allow others
to run. But if a thread or process
doesn't finish its current task before
its quantum expires, a hardware timer
triggers an interrupt that preempts the
process, meaning the OS pauses it and
reallocates the CPU to something
else. So if a data modification takes
longer than one time quantum, the data
will inevitably enter an invalid state
because at least one interruption is
guaranteed.
However, that doesn't mean shorter
operations are safe. Even if a data
modification completes in less than one
time quantum, race conditions can still
occur. Why? Well, for starters, if the
operation begins near the end of a time
quantum, it's highly likely to be
interrupted. But beyond timing issues,
the CPU can be interrupted by many other
events that aren't tied to theuler.
timers set by other processes. A user
pressing a button in a UI, an incoming
network packet. There are all kind of
events that trigger interrupts. And
interrupts regardless of their origin
can preempt the currently running
thread, even if it's time quantum hasn't
expired. And unfortunately, we can't
prevent those events from occurring. At
least not without making the system less
responsive to the very events those
interrupts are meant to handle. But can
we at least try to prevent them from
corrupting our data?
Let's go back to our example and try.
Before continuing, consider giving this
video a like. It helps others discover
my content, which by the way is
completely
free. What if we introduce a control
variable, a flag that indicates whether
the shared data is currently being
modified. For example, one means
writing, zero means not writing. With
this setup, threads that want to read
from the shared string can first check
the flag to see if the writer thread is
currently modifying
it. Now, while this might sound like a
good idea, we need to be cautious
because the moment this control variable
is shared between threads, it becomes
shared data and is therefore also
vulnerable to race
conditions. Setting or checking a
variable's value is not always atomic.
On some architectures, writing to a
variable may be atomic, but reading and
comparing its value almost never is.
This typically involves loading the
variable's value from memory into a
register, comparing that register's
value to some constant or expected
value, then acting on the result of that
comparison. Imagine this situation. A
reader thread checks the flag. It loads
the value into a register but right
after the comparison it gets
interrupted. Then the writer thread sets
the flag to one and starts modifying the
shared string but it also gets
interrupted before
finishing. Then when the reader thread
is dispatched again, its state is
restored. So it continues right where it
left off still holding the old value of
the flag in its register. Since this
thread fetched the value of the flag
before the writer thread modifies it,
the comparison is now based on an
outdated value. As a result, the thread
mistakenly believes it's safe to read
the shared string even though the data
is in an invalid state and our variable
didn't really help that
much. So unless we really know what
we're doing, using regular variables as
flags to control access to shared data
should be avoided. The reason I bring
this up is because there are some
classic software-based solutions like
this one called the Peterson solution
that rely on many subtle assumptions to
work correctly in very specific
situations. These include details like
software behavior, compiler
optimizations, and even hardware
architecture. I'll talk about this with
more details in my video about thread
synchronization. For now, let's keep
talking about race conditions. So far,
we've looked at the case where one
thread writes to shared data while other
threads only read from
it. But there are also cases where
multiple threads need to write to the
shared data at the same time. In these
cases, race conditions are just as
dangerous. Think about a program that
receives a number and finds how many
prime numbers exist between zero and
that number. Parallelism is used to make
the process faster so each thread can
run in a separate CPU core. To do this,
the threads use a shared counter, an
integer that gets incremented each time
a thread finds a prime
number. The problem is that in many
architectures, incrementing a value is
not an atomic operation. If two threads
in this example find prime numbers at
nearly the same time, we expect the
count to increase to
459. But since they are running in
parallel, they might both fetch the same
value, increment it independently, and
write the result back, resulting in the
counter only increasing by one, even
though two primes were found. And no
interrupt took part here. The race
condition happened because of the
parallel access to the shared variable.
But that doesn't mean things would have
gone better without parallelism. Here's
a simple scenario. Let's say the program
has already found 10 prime numbers.
Suddenly, five threads all find prime
numbers at roughly the same time. The
expected count afterward should be 15.
But watch what might
happen. Suppose the first thread fetches
the count and increments it, but is
interrupted right before writing the
result back to
memory. And then the other four threads
run without interruption. Each
successfully incrementing the count. So
the counter reaches 14.
Then the first thread resumes exactly
where it left off, right before the
instruction to store the incremented
value back to memory. But since that
value was calculated before the other
four threads incremented the counter, it
overwrites the updated result, causing
the count to drop from 14 back down to
11. And just like that, four correctly
detected prime numbers are lost.
This kind of behavior feels bizarre.
People usually think of computers as
being amazing at math, fast, smart,
sophisticated. But in truth, computers
are dumb. They don't recognize these
situations. They blindly follow
instructions even when those
instructions cause problems. And if
that's not bizarre enough, check this
out. If I run the same program multiple
times, I get a different result almost
every single time. sometimes even
getting the right result. Why? Because
the behavior of the program depends on
the timing and sequence of
uncontrollable events. There's no way to
predict when those events will occur.
That's what makes race conditions so
dangerous. It's called a race condition
because multiple operations race to
access or modify shared data and the
final result depends on which one
finishes
first. Finally, I want to emphasize
something that might seem
counterintuitive. The most dangerous
thing about race conditions is how rare
they are. In my server example, only 14
incidents occurred out of 85 million
requests. That's an incredibly small
probability. And that's what makes them
so hard to reproduce and debug. So the
next time your project uses concurrency,
remember if you're not careful, every
thread you spawn might be starting the
countdown on a time bomb. In the best
case scenario, your program will crash.
In the worst case, there's no telling
what it might end up doing. Fortunately,
computers provide tools to help us
prevent race conditions, but that's a
topic for a future episode. So, make
sure to subscribe. You don't want to
miss it. Thanks to Flexispot for
sponsoring this video. Don't forget to
check out the E7 Pro standing desk and
the treadmill. Both are linked in the
description below. See you in the next