this video was sponsored by
brilliant in the previous episode we
started talking about threads and it
seems you guys loved it today we're
continuing that discussion focusing
specifically on the role of threads in
systems with multi-core
processors hi friends my name is George
and this is core dumped before we dive
in just a quick announcement my friends
over at COD Crafters are giving away a
free lifetime subscription more details
at the end of the video all right let's
get started once again an important
concept we need to know in advance is
concurrency when we have multiple
processes but only a single CPU the
operating system can make it feel like
all those processes are running
simultaneously by alternating CPU access
between them at incredible
speed in the last episode we learned
about threads which are very useful when
writing programs for two key reasons if
one task in the same program takes a
long time to complete and another takes
only a few milliseconds concurrency
ensures the shorter task doesn't have to
wait a long time to start
running if a task is waiting for an IO
resource such as a file read or a
network response it can't use the CPU
during that time instead of letting the
CPU sit idle the operating system can
allocate that unused time to another
task that's ready to
run so threads are simply a way to tell
the operating system that multiple tasks
within the same process can run
concurrently they enable applications to
perform multiple tasks at the same time
for example in an email client app we
need to display the user interface on
the screen while listening for the user
keystrokes while uploading an attachment
like a photo from your file system while
performing grammar checking while
monitoring for incoming emails in order
to provide a good user experience none
of these tasks should wait to each other
to complete implementing concurrency has
some challenges though if the number of
concurrent tasks increases too much at
some point the system won't feel smooth
anymore even if the CPU alternates
between tasks extremely quickly there
comes a point where there are so many
tasks that it takes too long for each
one to regain access to the
CPU to address this there are three
possible solutions the most obvious
would be to Simply make the CPU faster
if the CPU can handle more work in the
same amount of time tasks can regain
access to it more quickly this solution
though isn't perfect because if we keep
it increasing the number of tasks will
eventually end up back where we started
too many tasks causing delays plus
making CPUs faster has become
increasingly difficult over the last
decade the second solution would be to
schedule CPU access in a more clever way
this is a more complicated solution that
deserves its own
video and the third solution like the
first one is a more like Brute Force
approach if a single processor can't
handle too many tasks no matter how fast
it is is just add more
processors this can be achieved in
several ways by adding more CPU sockets
to the same motherboard allowing for
multiple physical CPUs or by including
multiple processing units within a
single package or chip known as
multi-core
processors and though less common by
combining both multiple multi-core chips
in the same
motherboard the terminology around
processors can get a bit ambiguous the
term CPU is often used to refer to the
entire package or chip however each core
inside the package works as an
independent Processing Unit essentially
a CPU that shares some components like
the cache with other
cores in any case each core appears as a
separate processor to the operating
system so if you heard the term cores a
lot in this video you know what I mean
and before continuing a quick message
from brilliant one thing many of you
agree on is that traditional studying
can boring fortunately with brilliant
learning new things and developing new
skills doesn't have to mean endlessly
reading PDFs brilliant is designed to
offer small lessons that you can engage
with whenever you find the time making
learning a little each day both
enjoyable and convenient one of the best
brilliant features is the interactive
nature of their lessons which encourage
critical thinking skills through
problemsolving
activities this can help you a lot if
you want to become a better Problem
Solver which is what distinguishes good
from average Developers
its latest course thinking in code lays
down the foundational principles of
coding enabling you to adopt the mindset
of a programmer and you can pick other
topics such as applied Python and
creative coding you can get for free 30
days of brilliant premium and a lifetime
20% discount when subscribing by
accessing brilliant.org dumped or by
using the link in the description
below remember you can also support me
by liking this video it is free consider
an application with eight
threads on a system with a single
Computing core concurrency merely means
that the execution of the threads will
be interleaved over time because the
processing core is capable of executing
only one thread at a time but on a
system with multiple cores concurrency
takes on a new meaning here some threads
can truly run at the same time because
the system can assign each thread to a
separate core in other words with
multiple cores we're no longer just
dealing with concurrency we're dealing
with
parallelism notice the distinction
between concurrency and parallelism in
this discussion a concurrent system
supports more than one task by allowing
all the tasks to make some progress in
contrast a parallel system can perform
more than one task truly
simultaneously thus it is possible to
have concurrency without
parallelism one of the main advantages
in parallel systems is that the
smoothness of multitasking becomes less
reliant on Theus illusion created by
fast
interleaving and suddenly now it makes
even more sense why virtually all modern
operating systems consider threads
rather than processes as the basic unit
of
execution with multicore processors now
the standard threads within the same
process can take full advantage of
parallelism for us as programmers this
means that if we want to run tasks in
parallel all we need to do is declare
those tasks as concurrent using threads
the operating system will handle the
rest interleaving the CPU between
threads if no additional core is
available or assigning One Core to each
thread if the system runs in a
multi-core
processor this makes our programs more
portable since we don't have to compile
for a specific number of cores just
always consider two important things the
number of cores is fixed so creating a
thousand threads doesn't mean that a
thousand tasks will run in parallel
instead if the system has n cores up to
n threads can execute in parallel at any
given time and pay attention to this up
to n because threads compete for
resources even if we create the exact
number of threads as the number of cores
available threads from other processes
also need CPU time since one of the main
goals of the operating system is to
ensure Fair distribution of CPU
resources across all threads it limits
how many of our own threads can run in
parallel with that being said let's
discuss another reason why we might need
parallelism in our programs performance
this one is pretty obvious if we can
truly run more than one task at the same
time we can significantly reduce the
total time it would take to complete
those tasks compared to running them
sequentially on a single core
system in general there are two types of
parallelism data parallelism and task
parallelism data parallelism focuses on
Distributing subsets of the same data
across multiple Computing cores and
Performing the same operation on each
core
task parallelism involves Distributing
not data but tasks or threads across
multiple Computing cores in other words
each thread is performing a unique
operation but here we have multiple
scenarios different threads may be
operating on the same data or they may
be operating on different
data my plan for this video was to show
you some cool programming examples of
parallelism in action but well I messed
up my computer so we'll save that for
the next
episode before we wrap up this episode
though let's at least look at some
animated examples of
parallelism let's say we have a large
data set of numbers stored in an array
and our task is to find all the prime
numbers in that array this problem
requires us to iterate over the entire
array checking whether each number is
prime the key here is to understand that
the result of checking whether a number
is prime doesn't depend on the results
for any other numbers in the
array if we want to check whether the
last number in the array is prime we
don't need to wait for the earlier
numbers to be checked each number can be
processed
independently now if we have a four core
processor we can split the data into
four equal parts and assign each part to
a different core this is an example of
data parallelism because all cores are
performing the same operation on
distributed subsets of the data however
keep in mind that splitting the work
across four cores doesn't necessarily
mean we'll get four times the
performance for example I tested the
same example in my computer over 10
million times and here's the average
time it took to compute each
subset how much performance gain we can
achieve from parallel operations is
beyond the scope of this video but I'd
love to hear your thoughts on this so
your comments are welcome the most
upvoted comment will win a free lifetime
subscription to Cod Crafters this
Christmas now let's tweak the problem
say we're given the same data set but
this time we're tasked with finding the
lowest value in the array finding the
highest value calculating the arithmetic
mean of all the elements and checking if
the array contains the number
101 in this case it doesn't make sense
to split the data into subsets because
each of these operations requires access
to the entire data set to compute their
results but here's what we can do assign
each operation to a different core this
is an example of task parallelism
different threads working with the the
same data set but performing different
operations again using four cores
doesn't mean the process will be four
times faster but it's still a
significant Improvement on a single core
system we'd have to perform these four
operations one after the other with four
cores we can execute them simultaneously
reducing the total
time and that's about it for now there's
more content about threads coming soon
so make sure to subscribe because you
don't want to miss it don't forget to
leave a comment for a chance to win a
free lifetime subscription to Cod
crafters for those who aren't familiar
Cod Crafters offers challenge-based
courses where you can build tools like
git SQ light HTTP servers and even
interpreters from scratch using the
programming language of your choice I'll
leave a link in the description if you'd
like to support me by
subscribing if you enjoyed this video or
learned something please hit the like
button it is free and that would help me
a lot see you in the next one