this video was sponsored by
brilliant threads a subject in computer
science that many people are afraid of
and no wonder it seems
complicated okay no I'm just kidding
today we'll explore the fundamentals of
threads and how they leverage
concurrency to optimize computer
resource
utilization hi friends my name is George
and this is core
dumped as long as you get these four
Concepts threads are surprisingly easy
to
understand the premise is simple in
multi-process systems if we have one CPU
and multiple running processes the
operating system makes those processes
share the CPU by alternating access
between them this happens very fast so
fast in fact that the user is under the
illusion that all processes are running
simultaneously this technique is known
as concurrency and along with another
technique called CPU scheduling it is
responsible for the smooth multitasking
experience we enjoy on our Compu
computers but multitasking is only the
well-known purpose of concurrency and
CPU scheduling there's another less
obvious purpose maximizing the use of
Computer
Resources we'll dive deeper into this in
my video about CPU scheduling for now
what we need to know is that while a
process is often defined as a program in
execution it doesn't necessarily mean
the process is always using the CPU even
if the CPU is allocated to that process
for example a process might be waiting
for an IO resource in that scenario
allocating the CPU to that process would
be inefficient because it can't execute
instructions until the requested IO
resource is ready so instead it makes
sense to allocate the CPU to a different
process one that's ready to execute
instructions this is the second reason
why concurrency is so important it's not
just about running multiple programs at
once it's also about filling those
little gaps when a process can't use the
CPU by assigning it to another process
that
can up until now in this series we've
treated processes as the fundamental
unit of execution so we've assumed
there's nothing more basic than a
process for scheduling purposes so we
can't employ concurrency for executable
entities within the same process if this
sounds confusing what I'm trying to say
is that tasks within the same program
like two functions for example cannot
run asynchronously under the traditional
process
approach this makes sense if you've
watched my video on processes remember
each process has one program counter
that points to the instruction where it
is interrupted when the CPU is allocated
to other process but we cannot alternate
the CPU between two functions that are
part of the same process because with a
single program counter we can't keep
track where both are interrupted one of
the functions must wait for the other to
finish
executing but why would we need
concurrency inside a process in the
first place I mean if we wanted two
pieces of code to run concurrently and
Cooper operate couldn't we just put that
code in separate processes and use
interprocess communication to coordinate
their
actions well yes but using IPC isn't
always intuitive sometimes different
pieces of code that contribute to a main
goal are so correlated that putting them
in different processes just feels wrong
there are many situations where
concurrency within a process is
incredibly useful think about a server
that receives requests on Port 3000
where its sole purpose is to return a
profile image associated with each
client when a client sends a request the
server accepts it processes it by
searching and reading the image from
disk and once the image is loaded into
memory responds by sending the image
back to the
client because images are stored as
files on disk a very costly IO operation
is required to find the image and load
it in memory as a result processing a
request can take significantly longer
than simply accepting or responding to
it these steps are executed sequentially
and obviously take only a few
milliseconds so for a single client it
works just fine but with multiple
clients complications
arise if five requests arrive at
approximately the same time the server
will accept the first one quickly but
then spend significant time processing
it the second request will only be
handled once the first is completed and
so
on this creates a bottleneck with later
requests waiting a long time to be
attended
to now with five requests the bottleneck
is not that much of a problem but
imagine a thousand
requests and here we can see the real
problem notice the gray gaps in the
timeline these represent periods where
the CPU sits idle doing nothing this is
wasted computational time time that
could have been used to accept and begin
processing other clients
requests when one task is unable to
execute because another task is running
despite the two being independent we
call it a blocking effect for a long
time the solution to this problem was as
follows there's a main process that
listens for requests which we'll call
The Listener process every time a client
sends a request instead of handling it
directly The Listener process creates a
whole new process to attend to that
specific client this way if another
client sends a request it won't wait
until the previous request is completely
hand handled because the process that
listens and accepts the requests runs
concurrently with the one serving the
previous
client in other words this method allows
taking advantage of concurrency to use
the CPU as much as
possible while clever this approach
isn't perfect remember each process is
like a self-contained context with its
own properties including an address
space creating an entire process for
every client might work for a few
hundred clients but when scaling to
thousands it becomes inefficient in
terms of memory
usage additionally spawning a new
process is not a trivial operation it
consumes processing time so even though
the goal is to utilize idle CPU gaps a
portion of that time is actually spent
creating the new process
itself moreover if the server needs to
handle some kind of global State all
child processes must be synchronized to
keep track of it this requires some form
of IPC complicating the implementation
although processes are one of the most
important Concepts in computer science
they aren't perfect let's discuss the
solution after a quick message from
brilliant there's one fact we all know
about traditional studying reading books
might not always be the most effective
method but fortunately brilliant is here
to help with brilliant you have access
to dozens of different courses designed
by professionals and specifically
crafted so you can interact with
examples and improve your problem
solving skills through small ch
challenges remember one of the most
important aspects of being a good
developer is the ability to solve
problems the best part is you don't have
to spend hours because brilliant is
designed to help you learn a little
every day through small lessons even
better you can access it anywhere since
brilliant is available on your
phone you can access all sorts of
courses from math and data science
lessons to programming oriented courses
like thinking in code and how large
language models work you can try
everything brilliant has to offer for
free for a full 30 days and get 20% off
in your annual subscription by accessing
brilliant.org
dumped or by using the link in the
description
below and now back to the video since
the concept of a process is very useful
we can't just discard it but we can
modify it slightly to allow concurrency
within the executable code of a single
process remember in general terms a
process comprises an ID a program
counter a register set an address space
and other resources such as open files
and IO
devices as I explained earlier the main
limitation is that a single program
counter doesn't allow the process
control block the structure the OS uses
to represent processes to keep track of
more than one task at a time the
solution is to stop associating the
program counter directly with the
process and instead assign a program
counter to each inner executable entity
that we want to run concurrently within
the process these inner entities are
what we call
threads by no longer limiting each
process to a single program counter we
can now create a new thread whenever we
need code within the same process to run
concurrently this solves the blocking
problem without creating new processes
if one of the threads needs an IO
resource such as loading the contents of
a file into an array the other threads
can continue executing without being
blocked while threads share the entire
address space base of the process they
belong to they cannot share a CPU State
because threads are going to be
interrupted to allocate the CPU to other
threads we need to capture the state of
each thread so that when the CPU is
reallocated its state can be restored
therefore if each thread has its own
program counter it also must have its
own register set Flags accumulators Etc
essentially its own CPU
State and note that this includes a
separate stack pointer remember the
stack is a fast and efficient way to
organize and access local variables in
memory if two functions in the same
process run concurrently and share the
same stack they could easily overwrite
each other's
data hence each thread must have its own
stack and something that I want to make
sure is very clear is that the fact that
each thread has its own stack doesn't
mean that they cannot read from or write
to each others this makes perfect sense
if we can consider the address space as
a property of the process not the
threads since the stacks are located
within that shared address space nothing
prevents a thread from accessing another
thread
stack whether if you should do it or not
is a completely different discussion but
generally unless you really know what
you're doing it's best to avoid
accessing other threads Stacks
directly if threads within the same
process need to communicate by sharing
memory the Heap is more appropriate for
that since by its nature the data stored
in the Heap is not organized in in a
predictable way
anyway but even with the Heap caution is
still required if one thread is reading
from a block of memory while another is
writing to it the results can be
disastrous synchronizing concurrent
tasks is so critical that mechanisms for
doing so are implemented directly in
Hardware I'll cover this in a future
episode so make sure to
subscribe also because we are not
completely discarding the concept of a
process address spaces of different
processes are still isolated so while
sibling processes share memory by
default if threads from different
processes want to share data
interprocess communication is
needed replacing the traditional
multi-process approach with the
multi-threaded approach requires
reimplementing the process control block
the most obvious path here would be use
a second structure to represent threads
while implementation details can vary by
platform the most common approach is the
one used in the Linux kernel where both
processes and threads are represented by
the same structure called
task if you ask me I'd said this is a
perfect example of good naming and
programming because it abstracts away
the distinction between processes and
threads so instead of describing
concurrency as alternating CPU access
between processes threads or both we can
simply describe it as alternating
tasks this implementation is more
intuitive if we want to use a single
Schuler both for Threads and processes
regardless of the approach doing this
requires that every process has at least
one thread called the main thread
whenever a new process is created the
operating system automatically creates
This
Thread so even if a process doesn't rely
on multi-threading the operating system
can allocate the CPU to it by scheduling
its main
thread whether a process starts with a
fixed number of additional threads or
can spawn threads dynamically depends on
the operating system's implementation
most mainstream operating systems prefer
the dynamic approach where each process
starts as a single-threaded process and
additional threads are created at
runtime if
needed this of course increases the
complexity of the operating systems
internal implementation as it must
provide system calls for dynamic thread
creation but it's the preferred method
because in many cases it's impossible to
know at compile time how many threads
will be needed at
runtime okay that's a lot of information
before we discuss how all of this
applies to our server example there's
one last thing we need to know in many
implementations because the main thread
identifies the process it belongs to if
other threads are spawned and the main
thread terminates its execution the
execution of all the other threads will
immediately terminate there are multiple
ways to handle this problem but that's a
topic for another
video back to our server example with
the multi-threading approach we can
spawn a new thread for each incoming
client achieving a similar effect to the
multi-process approach but with far less
memory
consumption additionally there can be a
performance Improvement when using
threads because the system calls used to
create threads are generally completed
much faster than those used to create
new processes the reasons for this
should be obvious at this point and that
being said we should now Define what a
thread is but first we'll Define what a
thread is not a thread is not a function
and any code that a thread executes is
in the text section of the memory layout
of the process the thread doesn't
contain code it points to the code
through its program counter this means
multiple threads can point to the exact
same executable code this is precisely
what happens in our server example since
all the requests need to be handled in
the same way all the Handler threads
don't contain a function but rather
point to the same function in memory if
you're wondering if threads accessing
this memory area at the same time is
dangerous it's not
because executable code and constants
reside in the text and data sections two
regions that are never written
to all the information pertinent to a
specific thread generated at runtime
resides either on the stack or the Heap
so threads accessing the same executable
code concurrently is perfectly
safe perhaps this last part helps you
understand why in low-level languages
like C spawning a thread requires us to
pass a point pointer to a function as a
parameter this might seem confusing but
what we're actually doing is passing the
memory address where the code that the
thread will execute
begins so please don't misinterpret my
animations threads are not asynchronous
functions there are two ways we can
Define threads from the operating
systems point of view threads are what
processes were in our previous episode
the most basic unit of
execution from a developer's perspective
threads are a mechanism to tell the
operating system that certain pieces of
code inside our program can be executed
concurrently other interesting
definition that I've heard of is threads
can be seeing as lightweight processes
easier and faster to
create and remember everything I've said
in this video applies even to systems
that disposes of a single core
processor and let's wrap things up for
now in the next episode we'll discuss
the additional purpose of threads in
systems where the processor has multiple
cores the fundamentals of parallelism
if you learn something please hit the
like button it is free and that would
help me a lot see you in the next one