this video was sponsored by
brilliant if you copy an executable file
from a Windows machine to a Mac you'll
notice right away that the program won't
run on the Mac if I were to ask you why
you'd probably say it's because Macs use
Arm CPUs While most Windows machines use
Intel x86 CPUs a reasonable answer but
not the full story because if we go back
to 2019 when virtually all Max were
still running on Intel you would have
had the same problem in fact you can run
multiple operating system systems on the
same hardware for example I use both
Linux and windows on the same machine
but that doesn't mean I can run Windows
programs on Linux even though both use
the same
CPU but why isn't compiled code supposed
to translate directly into machine
instructions that the hardware can
execute if both operating systems are
running on the same CPU shouldn't the
program work on both this is a tricky
question to answer but that's exactly
what we're going to explore in this
video let's break it down hi friends my
name is George and this is core
dumped it turns out applications are not
only architecture specific they are also
operating system specific I want to
start this video by saying that the
world would be a much better place if
this limitation didn't exist if you ask
this question to a computer science
graduate they'll likely answer system
calls some of you might already have an
idea of where this is going but for
those unfamiliar with system calls I've
got what I believe is one of the best
videos on the topic on this channel but
for now I'll explain it as quickly as I
can general purpose operating systems
are designed to run multiple processes
simultaneously which means they must
share Hardware resources one of the most
important being the
CPU the CPU is the central piece of any
computer controlling nearly everything
this creates a potential security risk
because any process could theoretically
exploit the CPU to take control of the
system bypassing the operating system
system and Performing malicious actions
to prevent this CPUs operate in two
basic modes user mode and kernel mode in
kernel mode also known as privileged
mode the CPU can execute any instruction
in its instruction set granting it full
control over the system this includes
the ability to manipulate IO devices and
Hardware components like CPU timers or
the memory management unit in user mode
the CPU is restricted to a limited
subset of instructions this subset
allows it to perform tasks such as
moving and copying data performing
mathematical operations evaluating
conditions and running Loops while these
instructions are still very useful in
this mode the CPU cannot execute
privileged instructions required to
directly control
Hardware as you might have guessed user
programs run in user mode while the
operating system operates in kernel mode
the operating system uses privileged
instructions to ensure that no user
program can ever gain unauthorized
access to kernel mode this separation is
crucial for security but it introduces a
problem even for trivial tasks like
reading a file or more complex ones like
sending a message over the network user
programs need a way to access Hardware
the solution well if a user program
cannot manipulate Hardware it can
request the operating system to do it on
its
place for example if a program needs to
open a file and write to it it calls a
corresponding system function requesting
the operating system system to handle
tasks like locating the file on disk and
writing to
it and that's exactly what system calls
are system calls provide an interface to
the services offered by the operating
system by the way I'm not sure why the
book I use as a reference for operating
systems has dinosaurs on it but since
we're running JavaScript on the server I
guess we can't really complain anyway
system calls are usually available as
functions written in C or C++ and they
can be broadly categorized into six
major groups each operating system
provides its own unique set of system
calls and this is where compatibility
issues begin to arise in practice most
programs rely heavily on system calls
even the program you're using right now
to watch this video is constantly
invoking the operating system making
thousands of requests per minute for
various
services and you can check this yourself
if you're running Linux try this command
replacing the number with the process ID
of Interest this will display
information about your process and
you'll find a field called voluntary
context switches this value represents
the number of times the process has
invoked the operating system using
system calls to request services and
notice that the number is not small this
highlights the core problem user
programs are so dependent on system
calls that if another operating system
doesn't Implement them in exactly the
same way the program simply won't work
and it's not just about naming
differences even when system calls have
equivalents across operating systems
their functionality can vary
significantly for example on Windows you
can use the create process system call
which receives the path to the
executable file of a program to do
precisely that create a new process
straightforward right now if you're not
familiar with systems programming you
might assume the Unix equivalent the
fork system call also creates a new
process and it does but not just any
process instead it creates a clone of
the calling process with the only
difference being that the new process
has a unique process
ID so on Unix systems additional steps
are required to run a specific program
right after using Fork the child process
must invoke another system call such as
exec to replace its text section with
the contents of the executable file it
needs to run this topic is very
interesting and probably deserves its
own video let me know in the comments if
you'd like me to to cover it in a future
episode these kinds of design decisions
create significant differences between
operating systems on one platform a task
might require a single system call while
on another it might require several so
when compiled into machine code
platforms will generate different
instructions to achieve the same result
even though both programs are compiled
for the same CPU architecture those
extra instructions will lack meaning on
the other operating system leading to
undefined behavior and ultimately
crashes and it doesn't stop there even
if two operating systems defined the
exact same set of system calls other
low-level implementation details could
still create compatibility issues and
that's what we'll cover next after a
quick message from brilliant on New
Years we often resolve to learn new
skills as developers one of those should
definitely be improving our problem
solving abilities with brilliant you
gain access to dozens of interactive
courses designed by experts enabling you
to learn by doing rather than just
reading their first principles approach
helps you build a deep understanding
from the ground up each lesson is packed
with Hands-On problemsolving activities
that allow you to engage with Concepts a
method proven to be six times more
effective than simply watching lecture
videos brilliant is also available on
your phone making it easy to build real
knowledge in just a few minutes a day
unlike mindlessly scrolling through PDFs
their latest courses including applied
python creative coding and thinking in
code are perfect for building
foundational skills and learning real
world
applications helping you to develop the
mindset to think like a programmer and
begin creating complex programs to build
games and apps you can try for free 30
days of brilliant premium and get a 20%
discount on your annual subscription by
scanning the code on the screen or by
visiting brilliant.org
dumped also linked in the description
below and now back to the video when a
program needs to request something from
the operating system it triggers an
interrupt this interrupt causes the CPU
to switch to Kernel mode and hands
control over to the operating system on
architectures like x
8664 a special instruction called csol
is used for this purpose but once the
operating system takes control how does
it know which system call was requested
and if the system call requires
parameters how are those parameters
passed from the user program to the
operating system the common approach to
identifying system calls is to associate
each one with a unique number before
invoking the system call at the hardware
level the program writes the
corresponding number into a register
when the operating system takes control
it reads the value in that register and
consults a CIS call table to determine
the requested system
call on the source code of the Linux
kernel you can actually look up the
number associated with each system call
by checking architecture specific files
this also reveals just how many system
calls Linux supports the ones we've
discussed so far are only the most
commonly used
once again if two operating systems
don't provide the same system calls
using the exact same table the same
machine code could request entirely
different Services depending on the
operating
system let's assume both operating
systems use the exact same CIS call
table does that guarantee compatibility
unfortunately no if one of the operating
systems use different registers to
specify the CIS call number the program
would break running on that OS because
it would read the wrong register
identifying the wrong system call and
leading to undefined
Behavior okay but what if both systems
read from the same register does that
solve the problem still no many system
calls also require parameters and how
those parameters are passed depends on
the operating system some systems
require parameters to be stored in
registers While others write them to a
specific memory region or a combination
of both for instance on Linux if a
system call takes fewer than six
parameters they must be stored in
registers if more than six parameters
are needed the remaining ones are
written to
memory these seemingly small Details
Matter this is yet another example of
how a program designed for one operating
system might technically execute on
another OS running the same CPU but
behave unpredictably for example the OS
might expect parameters in memory while
the program has stored them in registers
or vice
versa if parameters are stored in memory
the method matters does the program use
the stack
or is there a specific memory location
for this
purpose if the parameters include
pointers the address width becomes
important these are just a few of the
low-level details that need to align
this set of conventions is known as the
application binary interface or ABI just
as an API defines functions at the
application Level an ABI defines how
different components of binary code
interact on a specific operating system
and architecture
and this is just in regard to system
calls yes we're not done yet even if all
the issues we've discussed were resolved
other low-level details could still
cause compatibility problems one of the
most significant factors is the
executable file format as we know an
executable file is what compilers
produce after translating source code
but this file doesn't just contain
instructions it also includes data and
metadata that allows the operating
system to load and execute the program
where in this CA of ones and zeros is
each part of the program located does it
look like this or like this or maybe
like this each operating system has
specific rules for this this structure
ensures that the executable can be
loaded and run properly by the operating
system while also supporting various
features like linking debugging and
dynamic Library usage if you're
interested in this topic I recommend
looking into the executable and linkable
format used on Linux and the portable
executable format used on Windows
another reason that comes to my mind is
runtime environments some programming
languages don't compile directly to
machine code they run on a virtual
machine or an interpreter instead this
means that as long as the virtual
machine is installed on the system the
same code can run across multiple
platforms ironically virtual machines
and interpreters are designed to bypass
many of the compatibility issues we've
discussed throughout this video however
modern applications are often built in a
modular way if all the modules are
compiled to machine code that's great
but if even one module depends on a
runtime and that runtime isn't installed
on the machine the entire application
might fail to
function I have nothing against
languages that require a runtime but
maybe we should stop writing critical
components of our systems in them then
again we're running JavaScript on the
server so I guess we can't really
complain let's wrap things up for now
there are more exciting topics coming
soon like CPU scheduling so make sure to
subscribe
you won't want to miss it if you enjoyed
this video or learned something new
please hit the like button it's free and
it helps me out a lot see you in the
next one